<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Caesars dialogue or A familiar communication containing the first institution of a subiect, in allegiance to his soueraigne</title>
            <author>Nisbet, E.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 195 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72932</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18432.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113170</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848409</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848409</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152155</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72932)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152155)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 325:9, 1973:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Caesars dialogue or A familiar communication containing the first institution of a subiect, in allegiance to his soueraigne</title>
                  <author>Nisbet, E.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 109, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Purfoot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: E.N., i.e. E. Nisbet.</note>
                  <note>In this state of the title page line 3 ends: Commu-.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 18432 on reel 325.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 325 and at reel 1973 (same copy filmed twice).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Allegiance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152155:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CAESARS DIALOGVE or A Familiar Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication containing the firſt Inſtitution of a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, in allegiance to his Soueraigne.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 22.21.</hi>
               </bibl> Giue therefore to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the things which are <hi>Caeſars.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by Thomas Purfoot. 1601.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:152155:2"/>
            <q>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Curſed be he, that curſeth thee: And Bleſſed be he that bleſſeth thee.</hi> 
               <bibl>Gen 27.20.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>But to take vengeance on him that doth euill. <bibl>Rom. 13.4.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Wherefore ye must be ſubiect, not becauſe of wrath onely, but alſo for conſcience ſake.</hi> 
               <bibl>Rom. 13.5.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>¶ The Miniſter of God, for thy wealth. <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 13.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Queen Elizabeth I</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152155:2"/>
            <head>TO All ſound <hi>Members</hi> of <hi>that</hi> bodie, <hi>whereof her</hi> ſacred <hi>Maiestie</hi> is Supreame head, <hi>Happineſſe</hi> Externall, Internall, <hi>Eternall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F we conſider</hi> howe much this admirablie-beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull <hi>frame</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi> the <hi>earth</hi> beeing adorned with ſweete ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>hearbes,</hi> fruit-bearing <hi>trees,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit variety of <hi>beaſts</hi> after their <hi>kind,</hi> the <hi>ſea</hi> repleniſhed with <hi>whales</hi> and <hi>fiſhes,</hi> after their <hi>kind,</hi> the <hi>ayre</hi> garni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with <hi>feathered fouls</hi> after their <hi>kind,</hi> the <hi>heauen</hi> beautified with the
<pb facs="tcp:152155:3"/>
               <hi>ſunne</hi> for the <hi>day,</hi> the <hi>Moone</hi> for the <hi>night,</hi> the bright-ſhining <hi>ſtarres,</hi> and all the <hi>hoſts</hi> thereof, excelleth that formeleſſe vaſtneſſe of the Poets <hi>Chaos,</hi> whereof ſaith the Scripture, <hi>The earth was without forme and voide, and darknes vpon the face of the deepe,</hi> then may we partly conceiue how much a <hi>Monarchie,</hi> which is amongſt gouernments as the <hi>Sunne</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the <hi>ſtars</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Homer Iliad. B.</note> Not good is the rule of many, Let there be one Lord, one King) where vnder one <hi>Caeſar</hi> the <hi>Nobilitie,</hi> the <hi>Cleargie,</hi> the <hi>Communaltie</hi> is prudently, iuſtly, happily gouerned, excelleth a bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh <hi>Anarchie,</hi> ſo hatefull to <hi>Moſes</hi> ſoule, that his death beeing by the Lord foretold him, not mentioning one word of his death he preſently brake out into a moſt <hi>patheticall</hi> praier for a Gouernour,<note place="margin">Num. 27.16.17.</note> 
               <hi>That the Congregation of the Lord might not be
<pb facs="tcp:152155:3"/>
as ſheepe which haue not a ſhepheard.</hi> The God of all <hi>glory</hi> (glorified, therefore be his glorious <hi>name</hi>) of his great grace &amp; mercy keeping vs from the <hi>one,</hi> hath ſo bleſſed vs with the <hi>other,</hi> as both <hi>neighbour,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote</hi> Nations crie out.<note place="margin">The happines of England. Pſal. 144.15.</note>
            </p>
            <q>O fortunatos nimium bona ſi ſua no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint anglos.</q>
            <p>Happy are the people that be in ſuch a caſe. That which <hi>abroad</hi> ſo many do <hi>admire,</hi> ſhall not euery one at <hi>home</hi> deſire to <hi>preſerue?</hi> Could <hi>he,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 8.12.</note> who was taken <hi>vp</hi> into <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> &amp; heard words which cannot be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, which are not <hi>poſsible</hi> for man to vtter, be himſelf deceiued<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> would <hi>he</hi> who was readie to giue his <hi>life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.3.</note> his <hi>life?</hi> yea his <hi>ſoule,</hi> for the good of <hi>others,</hi> deceiue <hi>others,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>If one member ſuffer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.26.</note> 
               <hi>all ſuffer with it, If one member be had in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, all the members reioyce with it?</hi> Are not wee <hi>members</hi> of the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:152155:4"/>
               <hi>bodie,</hi> of the ſame <hi>bodie politique,</hi> and <hi>temporall,</hi> there being to vs all one <hi>Queene:</hi> members of the ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die <hi>eccleſiastique</hi> and <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> their being <hi>one bodie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 4.4, 5, 6</note> 
               <hi>one ſpirit, one hope, one Lord, one faith, one Baptiſme, one God and Father of all, which is aboue all, and through all, and in you all?</hi> Who is there of you, of whom I am not to hope the beſt? Yet can I ſpeake onely for mine owne <hi>heart,</hi> for mine owne <hi>ſoule.</hi> Such liuely feeling hath my ſoule had of thoſe bonds wherewith as <hi>Country-men,</hi> wherewith as <hi>Christians</hi> wee bee combined, that I could not but <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,</hi> deſiring <hi>endeauour,</hi> endeauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>effect</hi> ſomewhat for the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Arcop.</note> If ſweet <hi>Iſocrates</hi> accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that <hi>not reuenewes and riches, not lawes and ordinances, but good nurture of youth make a Citie quiet and happy:</hi> If profound <hi>Aristotle</hi> affirmed that <hi>in vaine doe men make lawes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pol. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>if youth
<pb facs="tcp:152155:4"/>
be not brought vp in good manners:</hi> If diuine <hi>Plato</hi> auerred <hi>that ſmall need had his Common-wealth of lawes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De repub. li. 4</note> 
               <hi>by reaſon of the good diſcipline wherein his Citizens had bin nouriſhed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 22.6.</note> If <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> (who in reſpect of the others is as a <hi>Carbuncle</hi> amongeſt the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt gemmes) hath deliuered, <hi>Teach a child in the trade of his way, and when he is olde he ſhall not depart from it:</hi> What (eſpecially if ye looke ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon the <hi>proneſſe</hi> of ſome to be <hi>ſeduced,</hi> or vpon the <hi>malice</hi> of ſome <hi>mal-contents</hi> ſeeking to ſeduce, or vpon ſome, who from <hi>beyond</hi> the <hi>ſeas</hi> as <hi>Sathan</hi> from beyond the <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes</hi> raiſe vp <hi>windes</hi> to beat our <hi>houſes</hi> vpon our <hi>heads</hi>) what I ſay more <hi>conuenient,</hi> what more <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient,</hi> what more <hi>neceſſary</hi> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome <hi>inſtruction</hi> for our <hi>youth</hi> in their <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> to our <hi>Caeſar?</hi> An <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> leaſt <hi>England</hi> take vp that <hi>complaint</hi> of the Prophet,<note place="margin">Hoſea. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>My people are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed
<pb facs="tcp:152155:5"/>
for lacke of knowledge,</hi> a plaine <hi>inſtruction,</hi> leaſt our <hi>youth</hi> doe not conceiue it, a briefe <hi>instruction</hi> (intending hereafter for riper heads in another tongue more amplie to handle the like argument) leaſt few ſhould read it. But to whom then ſhall I tender and preſent it? May I to <hi>you</hi> moſt honorable <hi>Councellors?</hi> who am I that knowing your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips</hi> as <hi>Gedeliah</hi> did not alone <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi> ſerue,<note place="margin">2. King. 25.24</note> but alſo incite <hi>others</hi> to ſerue his <hi>King,</hi> not onely <hi>obey,</hi> but moſt principally draw <hi>others</hi> to <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> to our <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſhould inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt your <hi>graue conſultations</hi> with ſo <hi>ſleight a Schedule?</hi> yet haue moſt of your <hi>Honours</hi> (reſpecting the <hi>good end</hi>) moſt <hi>honourably</hi> approued it. <hi>Moſt</hi> and <hi>Right Reuerend Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> to whom God hath giuen his <hi>vrim</hi> and his <hi>thummim,</hi> may I preſent it to you? I am <hi>pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorum maximus, Apostolorum mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:152155:5"/>
I know <hi>yee</hi> put them in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, that they be <hi>ſubiect</hi> to the <hi>principalities and powers,</hi> and that they be <hi>obedient.</hi> Moſt graue <hi>Iudges</hi> and <hi>Maiestrates</hi> may I preſent it to you? The Right <hi>Honourable,</hi> who is among you as a <hi>Diamond</hi> ſet in <hi>Gould,</hi> hath in regard of the intent, giuen it his double approbation. You all knowing that law of the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> Common-wealth,<note place="margin">Deut. 17.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>That man that will doe preſumptuouſly, and will not hearken vnto the Prieſt (that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth before the Lord thy God to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter there) or vnto the Iudge, that man ſhall die, and thou ſhalt take away euill from</hi> Iſrael, <hi>So all the people ſhal heare and feare, and do no more preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</hi> Doe know what regard is to be had of <hi>Caeſar</hi> being the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Iudges</hi> Soueraigne. <hi>Tutors</hi> and <hi>instructors</hi> of our <hi>youth,</hi> dreſſors of the <hi>plants</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> ſhall I te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der it <hi>you,</hi> you being accounted moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb facs="tcp:152155:6"/>
               <hi>members</hi> of euery <hi>weale-pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like?</hi> In nothing more then this can you ſhew your loue to your <hi>cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try,</hi> nor diſcharge your <hi>dueties</hi> to your <hi>Soueraigne. Maiſters</hi> of families, and <hi>keepers</hi> of ſeruants, ſhall I tender it to <hi>you?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 4.1.</note> May I ſay in this reſpect, <hi>yee Maisters, doe that vnto your ſeruants which is iuſt and equall?</hi> Is it ſaid for <hi>food</hi> &amp; <hi>rayment</hi> only, or for <hi>ciuil</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> education alſo,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5, 8.</note> 
               <hi>That hee that prouideth not for his owne, and namely for them of his houſehold, hee denieth the faith, and is worſe than an infidell?</hi> Is not God highly diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with you for not inſtructing your houſeholds, who was ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſed with <hi>Abraham</hi> (if ye bee <hi>Abrahams</hi> children ye will doe the works of <hi>Abraham</hi>) for inſtructing of his <hi>houſehold?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 8.39. Gen. 18.17, 18 19.</note> Aſſure your ſelues, <hi>he</hi> who vpon the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>fleſh</hi> impoſed ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their enemies <hi>beasts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod 23.4, 5.</note> impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb facs="tcp:152155:6"/>
vppon the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> according to faith a far greater regard of their owne <hi>ſeruants:</hi> thoſe breath an <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable</hi> &amp; <hi>mortall</hi> life, theſe haue a <hi>reaſonable</hi> and an <hi>immortall</hi> ſoule: <hi>heires</hi> they be with you of the ſame <hi>ſaluation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fathers,</hi> ſhall I tender it to you? You remember who enioined you <hi>To teach your ſonnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4.9. Deut. 6.6.7, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>and your ſonnes-ſonnes:</hi> you remember who ſayde, <hi>Theſe wordes which I commaund thee this day, ſhalbe in thine heart: And thou ſhalt rehearſe them continuallie vnto thy children, and ſhalt talke of them when thou tarieſt in thine houſe, and as thou walkeſt by the way, and when thou liest downe, and when thou riſeſt vp. And thou ſhalt</hi> (not onelie for thy remembrance) <hi>binde them vpon thine hand, and betweene thine eyes,</hi> (but for thy children and ſeruants) <hi>write them vpon the postes of thine houſe, and vpon thy Gates.</hi> Thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:152155:7"/>
wordes of <hi>God</hi> teach vs our <hi>dutie</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> our <hi>dutie</hi> to our <hi>neighbours,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our <hi>neighbours,</hi> firſt to our <hi>ſuperiours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20.12.</note> amongeſt our <hi>ſuperiours,</hi> chiefly to our <hi>Caeſar,</hi> becauſe <hi>Caeſar</hi> is the <hi>father</hi> of the <hi>Countrey,</hi> the <hi>nourſing mother</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> Hence <hi>Salomon,</hi> hence <hi>Peter,</hi> hence <hi>Paule,</hi> hence <hi>Christ</hi> drew that which they haue taught vs for our <hi>duties</hi> to our <hi>Princes.</hi> As you loue your <hi>ſelues,</hi> as you loue your <hi>children,</hi> omit not <hi>this.</hi> Omit not <hi>this</hi> if you loue your <hi>children,</hi> for the ſame <hi>Adoniah,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> becauſe hee was his <hi>darling</hi> would not reprooue and correct with the <hi>rod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 1.6.</note> (I holde <hi>reproofe</hi> and <hi>correction</hi> to be either <hi>partes</hi> or <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purtenances</hi> of <hi>inſtruction</hi>) the ſame <hi>Adoniah,</hi> becauſe he proued a <hi>Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 2.25.</note> did <hi>Salomon</hi> (though hee were his <hi>brother</hi>) execute with the <hi>ſword.</hi> Omit it not, if you loue your <hi>ſelues,</hi> for, O howe <hi>heauie</hi> was the <hi>Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:152155:7"/>
that fell vpon the head of <hi>Eli.</hi> for omitting this <hi>dutie:</hi> for omitting this <hi>dutie</hi> vpon <hi>Eli, old Eli, Eli</hi> the <hi>high Prieſt, Eli</hi> who had iudged <hi>Iſrael</hi> fortie yeares,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.23, 24, 25.</note> 
               <hi>Eli</hi> who herein had done ſomewhat, O how <hi>heauie</hi> I ſay was the <hi>Iudgement</hi> that for omitting this <hi>dutie</hi> fell vpon his <hi>bead,</hi> when in one day <hi>Iſrael</hi> fled before the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam, 2.17, 18.</note> there was a great ſlaughter among the <hi>people,</hi> his two <hi>ſonnes</hi> were both ſlaine, the <hi>Arke</hi> of <hi>God</hi> was taken, <hi>himſelfe</hi> fell <hi>backward</hi> and brake his <hi>necke</hi> that he died. Better then that this ſhould befall, were it that the <hi>Romane law</hi> were receiued into <hi>England,</hi> whereby it was enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that, for the firſt <hi>offence,</hi> the <hi>child</hi> ſhould be <hi>admoniſhed,</hi> for the <hi>ſecond</hi> he ſhould be <hi>chaſtized,</hi> for the <hi>third</hi> he ſhould be <hi>hanged,</hi> and the <hi>father</hi> baniſhed. <hi>Mothers,</hi> whom <hi>nature</hi> or rather the <hi>God</hi> of nature, hath made moſt kinde to your <hi>children,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:152155:8"/>
let not your too great <hi>kindneſſe</hi> to <hi>them,</hi> be too <hi>great hurt</hi> to <hi>them,</hi> and too <hi>great</hi> hurt too <hi>you.</hi> The wiſeſt <hi>ſonne</hi> that by courſe of <hi>natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> euer any <hi>mother</hi> had hath left this leſſon for all mothers for euer,<note place="margin">Prou. 29.15.</note> A <hi>childe ſet at libertie ſhameth his mother.</hi> Thogh I tell you not either of that too <hi>wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonly brought-vp ſonne,</hi> who beeing led to <hi>execution</hi> by the clamor of his <hi>tongue,</hi> and ſharpeneſſe of his <hi>teeth,</hi> tooke irefull reuenge of his owne <hi>mother:</hi> or of that <hi>mother,</hi> who to maintaine her two <hi>ſonnes</hi> in <hi>drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> and <hi>gaming,</hi> defrauded her <hi>huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band</hi> in his <hi>life,</hi> ſoone after his <hi>death</hi> with her owne eies behelde them both (robbing following vpon rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) <hi>openly executed,</hi> the <hi>one</hi> with the <hi>ſword,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> with the <hi>rope.</hi> Yet giue me leaue to tell <hi>you,</hi> that if <hi>Aretia</hi> taught her ſonne <hi>Philoſophie:</hi> if <hi>Cornelia</hi> taught her ſonnes the <hi>Latin eloquence:</hi> If <hi>Zenobia</hi> taught
<pb facs="tcp:152155:8"/>
her ſonnes the <hi>Greeke, Latin,</hi> and <hi>Egyptian</hi> tongues:<note place="margin">Prou. 31.1.</note> if <hi>Bethſaba</hi> taught her ſonne a <hi>propheſie:</hi> you are to ſee that your <hi>children</hi> learne both thoſe <hi>principles</hi> of <hi>religion</hi> alreadie publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that they may <hi>giue</hi> to <hi>God</hi> thoſe things that are <hi>Gods,</hi> and this <hi>inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> of a <hi>Subiect,</hi> that they may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the wil of <hi>God</hi> expreſſed in the <hi>word</hi> of God, <hi>Giue vnto Caeſar the things which are Caeſars,</hi> So ſhall <hi>you,</hi> ſo ſhall <hi>they</hi> pleaſe both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Caeſar. Children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preach. 12.1.</note> and all ſortes of <hi>youth, Remember your Creator in the dayes of your youth:</hi> and in the dayes of your youth as carefully learne to <hi>honour thoſe that are ſet ouer you by God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20.12.</note> as you deſire earneſtly that a <hi>long life,</hi> ſhould bee giuen you of God. Laſt of all, I ſay to <hi>all: If there bee any conſolation in Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>if any comfort of loue, if any felowſhippe of the Spirit, if any compaſsion and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, fulfill my ioy:</hi> As we are become a
<pb facs="tcp:152155:9"/>
               <hi>happie Nation</hi> by the <hi>gouernment</hi> of our <hi>Caeſar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Barue. 1.11.</note> ſo let <hi>vs</hi> and <hi>ours,</hi> perform all <hi>dutifull allegiance</hi> to our <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>pray,</hi> and <hi>pray feruently,</hi> and <hi>pray continually,</hi> that her <hi>daeys vpon earth</hi> may be as the <hi>dayes</hi> of <hi>heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the L. <hi>if you be Caeſars in the L. E.N.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152155:9"/>
            <head>CAESARS DIALOGVE, <hi>or,</hi> a familiar communication, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the firſt inſtitution of a Subiect, in allegiance to <hi>his Soueraigne.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage>
               <list>
                  <item>Father.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sonne.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y ſonne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A father.</note> at thy birth I receiued thée as a <hi>gift</hi> of the Lord, ſince thy birth, I made thée a chiefe obiect of my care, it is thy part hereafter to become while I liue,<note place="margin">Eccle. 30.4</note> the ſtaffe of mine age, and when I am dead,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 18, 18.</note> to be ſo like me (whereof I more eſtéeme then of the pillar of <hi>Abſolon</hi>) that I ſhall not ſéeme to be dead.<note place="margin">Prou. 31, 2.</note> But <hi>O my ſonne, but O the Sonne of my loynes, but O the Sonne of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires,</hi> if by diſloyaltie thou euer tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152155:10"/>
the <hi>gift</hi> of God into a <hi>iudgement</hi> vpon my head,<note place="margin">The Fathers Care.</note> If thou changeſt the <hi>cares</hi> of my head into <hi>thornes</hi> to my heart. If thou bringeſt my gray head with <hi>ſorrow</hi> vnto the graue, if thou diſhonoureſt my <hi>name,</hi> attainteſt my <hi>blood,</hi> ouerthroweſt my <hi>houſe,</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deare father vnworthie were I of life, if I ſhould ſo highly offend him who (next to God) gaue me life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ſonnes acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> 
                  <hi>and whom God himſelfe hath commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me to honour.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>Then ſwéete <hi>Sonne</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print now in thy heart, and expreſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in thy life, that ſhort <hi>charge</hi> of our ſwéeteſt Sauoiur,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Giue vnto Caeſar the thinges which are Ceſars, and giue vnto God, thoſe things which are Gods.</hi> Of giuing vnto God the things that are Gods (the performance of which dutie is euer to be preferred before the ſafetie of thy life) thou vſually heareſt both of thy <hi>maiſter,</hi> from whome as <hi>Xenocrates</hi> Diſciples of <hi>riotous and diſſolute,</hi> became <hi>modeſt and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate,</hi> I expect thou ſhouldeſt dayly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, not onely better lettered in thy <hi>booke,</hi> but alſo more reformed in thy
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152155:10"/>
                  <hi>life,</hi> and alſo of our <hi>Ambaſſadours</hi> for Chriſt, as well in their Catechiſings,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.20.</note> as in their Sermons. Now therefore as my other affaires will giue mee leaue, I will ſomewhat inſtruct thée of giuing vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the things which are <hi>Caeſars.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Becauſe as the Kinges of <hi>Egypt,</hi> were alwayes called <hi>Pharaos,</hi> ſo I thinke the Romane Emperours were euer called <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and the Romane Emperours were moſt high &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie princes, I take it, that by the name of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> you vnderſtand our high, gracious, and imperiall Soueraigne.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>Our Soueraigne indéed, my <hi>ſonne,</hi> do I vnderſtand, who nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as the <hi>Rhaguſians</hi> to the <hi>Turke,</hi> paying pencion to any, nor as <hi>Bologna</hi> from the <hi>Pope,</hi> expecting protection from any, nor as the knights of <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> do of the <hi>Caſtilian,</hi> holding in ſée and fealtie of any, nor as the Dukes of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> to the Colledges of <hi>ſeuen</hi> and <hi>ten,</hi> and to the <hi>Signiorie of Gentlemen,</hi> (God and her owne conſcience excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) being countable to any, but being ſo abſolute a <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> and ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152155:11"/>
an <hi>Empreſſe,</hi> truly meriteth the true title of <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Since I haue heard there haue beene ſome in <hi>Germanie,</hi> but I hope there be none in <hi>England,</hi> who ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the Scripture (but I thinke Spider-like they gather poiſon where the Bee would gather honie) that we are not to be ſubiect to the authoritie of men: I pray you ſhew mee ſince the Sonne of God hath ſaid, that <hi>no man can ſerue two maiſters,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 6, 26</note> 
                  <hi>how I can ſerue both God and <hi>Caeſar?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>My <hi>ſonne,</hi> as the ſouldior may at one time, in the ſame ſeruice fulfill his dutie both to the <hi>Captaine</hi> of his band, and the <hi>Generall</hi> of the field, (the one of them being not deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the other, but deputed by the other,) ſo the ſubiect may in his whole life ſerue his <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> of kings, becauſe <hi>Caeſar</hi> hath not (though the Poet ſung ſo) <hi>commaund</hi> diuided with God: but (for the Scriptures teach ſo) <hi>deputed</hi> of God. And therfore my <hi>ſon,</hi> becauſe as among the <hi>Iſraelites Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> told <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> that they tooke too much
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152155:11"/>
vpon them,<note place="margin">Num. 16, 3</note> ſéeing all the congregation is <hi>holy,</hi> euery one of them, &amp; the Lord is among them: So there are among Chriſtians which (as S. <hi>Iude</hi> ſaith) <hi>Deſpiſe gouernment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iude 8</note> 
                  <hi>and ſpeake euill of them that are in authoritie,</hi> (as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith) <hi>are preſumptuous,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2, Pet 2.10</note> 
                  <hi>and ſtand in their owne conceit, and feare not to ſpeake euill of them that are in dignitie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2, Tim. 3, 4</note> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be traitors, headie, high minded;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2, Pet. 3, 17</note> ſéeing thou knoweſt theſe things before, beware leaſt thou be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo plucked away with the errour of the wicked. Call to minde the charge of the Apoſtle of the circumciſion. <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mit your ſelues to al maner of ordinance of man for the Lords ſake,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet, 2, 13.14.</note> 
                  <hi>whether it be vnto the king, as vnto the ſuperior, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the gouernors, as thoſe that are ſent of him.</hi> Call to mind the doctor of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, both his <hi>decree,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1 Titus 3.1</note> and his <hi>memen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> his <hi>decree, Let euery ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers;</hi> his <hi>memento, <hi>Put them in minde that they bee ſubiect to the higher powers, and that they be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient.</hi>
                  </hi> Call to minde (whereof I gaue thée a former charge) that thriſe recou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted precept of the King of kings,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152155:12"/>
and Lord of Lordes: <hi>Giue vnto Caeſar the things which are Caeſars.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 22.21, Mark. 12 17. Luke. 20.25</note> And God giue thee ſuch grace as thou maiſt hearken to the <hi>charge,</hi> obey the <hi>decree,</hi> remember the <hi>memento,</hi> and fulfil the <hi>precept.</hi> From the which that thou mayſt neuer ſlide, either by the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy owne heart, or the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of men, or the ſuggeſtion of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, I will only (ſince the wiſeſt either of kings or men affirmeth that a <hi>three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Cable</hi> is not eaſily broken) ſhewe thée a <hi>foure-folde Cable,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Preach. 4, 12</note> which may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hold thy whole heart and ſoule in all allegiance to thy <hi>Soueraigne.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1 <hi>The founder and confirmer of</hi> Caeſar.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 13, 1.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2 <hi>The haynouſneſſe of the crime of diſloyaltie to</hi> Caeſar.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3 <hi>The puniſhments of diſloyaltie to</hi> Caeſar.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4 <hi>The rewardes of loyaltie to</hi> Caeſar.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who I pray you, is founder and confirmer of <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>Neither any <hi>wicked ſpirit,</hi> nor <hi>mortall man,</hi> nor <hi>heauenly An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell,</hi> but God himſelfe, <hi>God himſelfe</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152155:12"/>
is the <hi>founder</hi> and <hi>confirmer</hi> of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p n="1">1. Cable of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance is Caeſars foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
                     <p>Effectual mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues vnto al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, be the attributes of God, and his benefits to vs.</p>
                     <p>Attributes of God.</p>
                     <p>Heb 4.13. 1. Infallible knowledge. Rom. 11, 33. 2. Inexplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</p>
                  </note> In <hi>Caeſars</hi> founder conſider the <hi>attributes</hi> of him, and his <hi>benefites</hi> to vs: Among the attributes of him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider his <hi>knowledge</hi> infallible, his <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence</hi> inexplicable, his <hi>iudgements</hi> ineuitable, his <hi>decree</hi> immutable, his <hi>wrath</hi> terrible, his <hi>loue</hi> vnſpeakable, his <hi>mercie</hi> deſyrable. His knowledge infallible, <hi>There is not any creature which is not manifeſt in his ſight, all things are naked, and open vnto his eies. O the deepneſſe of the riches both of the wiſdome and knowledge of God.</hi> His prouidence inexplicable, hee reacheth (with means, without means, againſt meanes) <hi>from one end to another migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, and ordereth all things comely.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Wiſd. 8.1.</note> His iudgements ineuitable,<note place="margin">Iob 10, 7. Ineuitable iudgements. Pſal, 139.6, 7, 8, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>None can deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer me out of thy hand. Whither ſhall I go from thy ſpirit, or whither ſhall I flie from thy preſence? If I aſcend into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, thou art there, if I lie down in hell, thou art: here, let mee take the wings of the morning, and dwell in the vttermoſt parts of the ſea, yet thither ſhall thine hand lead me, and thy right hande holde me.</hi> His decrée immutable,<note place="margin">Iames 1.17.</note> with him
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152155:13"/>
is no variableneſſe, neither ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by turning.<note place="margin">Num. 23, 19 Immutable decree.</note> 
                  <hi>God is not as man that he ſhould lie, nor as the ſon of man that he ſhould repent: hath he ſaid, and ſhall he not do it? And hath he ſpoken, and ſhall he not accompliſh it?</hi> His wrath terrible,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.18 Terrible wrath.</note> 
                  <hi>The wrath of God is reuealed from heauen againſt all vngodlineſſe and vnrighteouſneſſe of men, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the truth in vnrighteouſneſſe.</hi> His loue vnſpeakable,<note place="margin">1. Iohn, 4 10 Vnſpeakable loue.</note> 
                  <hi>Herein is loue, not that we loued God, but that he loued vs, and ſent his ſonne to bee a reconciliation for our ſinnes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioel. 2.13 Deſireable mercie. His benefites. Election. Reuel. 1, 4 Gen. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 27. Creation. Iohn 3.16 Redemption.</note> His mercie deſyrable, <hi>Hee is gracious and mercifull, ſlowe to anger, and of great kindneſſe.</hi> His be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites to vs, <hi>God himſelfe choſe vs before the foundation of the worlde, that we ſhould be holie:</hi> When we were nothing, <hi>Created vs in his owne image:</hi> When we were worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing, <hi>So loued vs, that hee gaue his onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſonne, that ſo many as beleeue in him ſhould not periſh, but haue euerlaſting life:</hi> In this worlde <hi>externally,</hi> hath for our ſakes ſent out the Aungels to miniſter,<note place="margin">Preſeruation. Heb. 1, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>internally,</hi> hath giuen vs the ſpirit of adoption, whereby wee crie
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152155:13"/>
                  <hi>Abba</hi> father,<note place="margin">Sanctification Rom. 8, 15, 16.</note> the ſame ſpirite beareth witneſſe with our ſpirit, that wee are the children of God,<note place="margin">Glorification. 1. Cor. 2.9.</note> againſt the world to come, hath prepared for vs the things, which eye hath not ſeene, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eare hath heard, neither came in-the heart of man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Being bound by ſo many bonds to the ſeruice of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aſſurance that God inthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Caeſar, a great motiue to allegiance.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſhould euer moſt willingly ſerue <hi>Caeſar,</hi> if it would pleaſe you to ſhewe ſome proofe that <hi>Caeſar</hi> is enthroned by God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>Proofe of that doth the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhewe both by plaine <hi>teſtimonies,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Double profe that God in throned Caeſar. Plaine teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. And thoſe bee affirmatiue, Wiſd. 6, 23</note> and euident <hi>arguments:</hi> By plaine te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, and that both <hi>affirmatiuely,</hi> and <hi>negatiuely:</hi> affirmatiuely, So ſaith the Wiſeman, <hi>Giue eare ye that rule the multitudes, &amp; glorie in the multitude of the people, for the rule is giuen you of the Lord, and power by the moſt high: vncreated wiſdome, by me kings raigne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 8.15</note> 
                  <hi>and princes decree iuſtice:</hi> The prophet, <hi>He taketh away kinges,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 2, 21. Rom. 13, 1 Or negatiue.</note> 
                  <hi>hee ſetteth vp kings:</hi> the Apoſtle, <hi>The powers that be, are ordained of God. Negatiuely,</hi> So Chriſt to his diſciples,<note place="margin">Math. 10, 29</note> 
                  <hi>Not a Sparrow falleth to the ground without your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152155:14"/>
So <hi>Chriſt</hi> to <hi>Pilate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 19, 11 Rom. 13, 1.2. euident ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou couldeſt haue no power at all againſt me, except it were giuen thee from aboue.</hi> So Saint <hi>Paul, There is no power but of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe euident teſtimonies be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient proofes: but yet what I beſeech you be the other arguments?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">His ſpirit al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering their hearts. 1. Sam. 10.9 1. Sam. 16.19</note>His <hi>ſpirite</hi> altering their hearts. Soone after <hi>Saul</hi> was anointed king, God gaue him another heart. From the day that <hi>Samuel</hi> anointed <hi>Dauid,</hi> the ſpirit of the Lord came vpon <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>His eyes ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing their thrones. Iob. 36.7. Their end. Rom. 13.6. The title he taketh of them to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Pſal. 10.16. The title he giueth them with his own mouth. Pſal. 82, 6. His direction of their hearts tongues, and hands.</p>
                  </note> His <hi>eies</hi> ſecuring their thrones. <hi>His eies are with kings in the throne, where he placeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for euer, thus they are exalted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their <hi>ende</hi> beeing to do him ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: <hi>They are Gods miniſters apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues for the ſame thing.</hi> The <hi>title</hi> that he taketh from them to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>The Lord is king for euer and euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>title</hi> he with his own mouth gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to them, <hi>Ego dixi,</hi> not any <hi>creature</hi> in heauen or earth, but the <hi>Creator</hi> of heauen &amp; earth, he ſaith, <hi>I haue ſaid, ye are Gods.</hi> The kings <hi>heart</hi> is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hand of the Lord, he turneth it whenſoeuer it pleaſeth him. In the kings <hi>heart</hi> is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152155:14"/>
the <hi>will</hi> of God,<note place="margin">Prou. 21.1. Prou. 16.10. 2. Chro. 19.9.</note> in the kings <hi>mouth</hi> is the <hi>decree of God,</hi> in the ſigning of the kings <hi>hand,</hi> the <hi>iudgements</hi> of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>More cleare is it then the light,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Obiection. Anſwere. Euill
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Of Crime</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Of Paine.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
Euill of crime is not of God Hee needeth it not. Gen. 17.1. He forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it. 1. Iohn. 3.4. He licenceth no man to do it.</p>
                     <p>Ecclus. 15.20. He hateth all that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit it. Pſal. 55. Heaccurſeth it Deut. 28.15. He ſeuerely puniſheth it. The Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent hee eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth for it. Math. 25.41.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that all good princes are of God, but ſince euery euill prince is ſo great an euill, ſo great a plague, how can he be of God, who is the onely ſpring from whence all goodneſſe flow?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>There is an euill of <hi>Crime,</hi> and an euill of <hi>paine,</hi> the euill of crime is <hi>ſinne,</hi> the euill of paine is the <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment</hi> of Sinne. The euill of crime is not of God. God béeing all ſufficient, doth not need it. It is the tranſgreſſion of the <hi>Lawe,</hi> therefore he doeth forbid it; hee commaunded no man to doe it, neither gaue hee any man a licence for it; hee hateth all them that commit it: he accurſeth it, he (I call to witneſſe <hi>Adam</hi> thruſt out of Paradiſe, the <hi>olde world</hi> drowned with the floud, <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomor</hi> flaming with fire, the <hi>Sonne of God</hi> for the ſinnes of men, giuing vp his Ghoſt vpon the Croſſe) ſeuerely puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth it; and in the impenitent he <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally</hi> condemneth it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152155:15"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>The euill of Pain is of God Eſay. 45.7. Amos. 3.6. A good King cometh from the right hand of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</p>
                     <p>An euil king from the left hand of Gods Iuſtice. Hoſea. 13.11.</p>
                     <p>For the ſins of the people, hee ſuffereth the hipocrite to raigne.</p>
                     <p>Iob. 34.30. 2. A good King to fal. 2 Sam. 24.1. 1 Cron. 21 1. 3. Chaungeth Kings.</p>
                     <p>Prou. 28.2. 4. Puniſhe Prince &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
                     <p>1 Sam. 12.25. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Bringeth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill from the good Prince vpon the euill.</p>
                  </note>The euill of <hi>Paine</hi> is the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſin, and this is throwne from the <hi>Throne</hi> of God vppon the heads of wicked men. I, ſayth the Lord, <hi>forme the light, and create darkneſſe, I make peace and create euill;</hi> the Prophet of the Lord, <hi>ſhall there bee euill in a Cittie and the Lord hath not done it?</hi> As a good Kinge commeth from the right hand of Gods <hi>mercie,</hi> ſo an euill King from the left hande of Gods <hi>Iuſtice.</hi> Sometimes for our ſinnes hee giueth an euill Kinge, <hi>I gaue thee a Kinge in mine anger:</hi> he maketh the Hipocrite to raigne for the ſinnes of the people, for the ſinnes of the people he ſuffereth a good King to fall: Iſraell hauing ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt God, God ſuffered <hi>Sathan</hi> to put into <hi>Dauids</hi> heart the numbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the people: for the ſinnes of the people hée changeth Kinges: for the tranſgreſſion of the Lande there are many Princes thereof. For the ſins of Prince, and people, God puniſheth the Prince and people. <hi>If ye doe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly ye ſhall periſh, both yee and your Kinge:</hi> If thou béeſt <hi>euill,</hi> euill ſhall come to thée from him, though hee bee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152155:15"/>
                  <hi>good:</hi> for he is the Miniſter of God, <hi>to take vengeance on him that doth euill.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.4. Titles of euill princes ſhewe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of gods Iuſtice.</note> Since therefore euerie Prince both <hi>good</hi> and <hi>bad</hi> is of God (therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth hee <hi>Aſhur</hi> the Rod of his wrath, &amp; the ſtaffe in their handes his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: therefore calleth he <hi>Nabuchodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nozor</hi> king of <hi>Babell,</hi> his ſeruant,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Eſay. 10.5. Rodde of his wrath. Ieremie 27.6. ſeruant.</p>
                     <p>Eſay 45.1. annointed. Flagellum Dei. Ira Dei. 1 Peter. 2.18.</p>
                  </note> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore calleth hée <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Annointed, therefore (I take it, did <hi>Attila</hi> call him ſelfe Gods ſcourge, and <hi>Themir-cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clu,</hi> vulgarly <hi>Tamberlaine</hi> himſelfe the wrath of God) as <hi>Peter</hi> commaundeth ſeruants to bee ſubiect to their Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with all feare, not onely to the good and courteous, but alſo to the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: ſo I aduiſe all Subiects to bée ſubiect to their Princes with al feare, not onely to the good and gracious, but alſo,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.2. Iohn. 14.15.</note> though they be as cruell as <hi>Nero,</hi> (for whome Saint <hi>Paule</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to pray) for as God the <hi>Sonne</hi> ſayth, <hi>If ye loue me keepe my comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements,</hi> So mee thinke God the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> from whome all power is giuen, God the <hi>Sonne</hi> by whom all kings doe raigne, God the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> framing the heartes, tongues, and handes of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152155:16"/>
Princes, ſay to all worſhippers of the Deitie,<note place="margin">
                     <p>The Iniunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Trinity to all worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the Deitie. Rom. 13.2. The 2 Cable The haynouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie.</p>
                     <p>What a pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, VVhat a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth.</p>
                     <p>Thucid. In Rebellion all kinde of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</p>
                     <p>Rebellion the chanell where the 7. Capitall Sinnes doe flowe.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>If ye loue me keepe my or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Though this firſt Cable be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to hould any heart in Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, which hath any anchor-hold in God, I deſire to heare ſomewhat of the greatneſſe of the Crime of <hi>Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> that the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of it, may make me to abhorre it.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>Abhorre it? abhorre it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede my <hi>Sonne,</hi> for where as <hi>a well gouerned Kingdome</hi> reſembleth the frame of the world, yea the Kingdome of Heauen, where the holy Angels, &amp; bleſſed ſoules glorifying God, day and night liue in <hi>eternall bliſſe:</hi> ſo <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion</hi> reſembleth not only the <hi>Chaos,</hi> but Hell it ſelfe, where is no <hi>order,</hi> but euerlaſting <hi>horror,</hi> that well ſaide the greeke <hi>Hiſtoriographer</hi> in that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, <hi>in Rebellion is all kinde of euill:</hi> It is not one ſinne, but the <hi>ſincke</hi> of all ſinne, the <hi>Sea</hi> of all miſchéefe, will you ſée the <hi>ſeauen Capitall</hi> ſinnes? Is not proude <hi>ambition,</hi> or ambitious <hi>pride</hi> the firſt ſparke of that fire? Doth not <hi>enuie</hi> blow the coale? Doth not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152155:16"/>
                  <hi>wrath</hi> dayly increaſe the flame? Doe they not ſéeke to bring al into the noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome aſhes of <hi>ſlouth, gluttony,</hi> &amp; <hi>wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnnes?</hi> Will you looke into all the Commandements of God,<note place="margin">Rebellion tranſgreſſeth all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note> ought wee not to honour the onely God? but of <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Seditious</hi> perſons to their <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> whom the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> hath made a God on earth,<note place="margin">Pſa. 82.6.</note> Doth God himſelf ſay,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 8.7.</note> as of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> he did to <hi>Samuel, They haue not caſt thee away, but they haue caſt me away, that I ſhould not raigne ouer them.</hi> Ought we not to vſe the <hi>worſhip</hi> of God that God hath preſcribed, to the <hi>end</hi> hee <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> hath preſcribed it?<note place="margin">1. kin. 12.28.</note> but the <hi>Rebell</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reiecteth it, or bringeth in as <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam</hi> the Calues, his owne deuiſes, or pretendeth ſacrifices and ſermons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (O what affinitie hath <hi>Religion</hi> with <hi>Rebellion</hi>) when <hi>Ahithophell</hi> is ſent for, &amp; the <hi>treaſon</hi> is great?<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.12.</note> Ought we to take the <hi>name</hi> of the Lord in <hi>vaine?</hi> but if it be ſo <hi>odious</hi> in the ſight of God,<note place="margin">Eze. 17.15.16.17</note> for a <hi>king</hi> to violate his oath to a <hi>King</hi> that hath vanquiſhed him, how <hi>odious</hi> and execrable is it for a <hi>ſubiect</hi> to violate his oath to his naturall <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne?</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:152155:17"/>
For the <hi>Sabaoth,</hi> how do they hallow it, who either beginning <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> or continuing Rebellion vpon that day, doe themſelues prophane it, and hinder others from the vſuall ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it: Can neither Gods owne <hi>example,</hi> who reſted the ſeuenth day, nor his <hi>precept,</hi> who commaunded vs to hallow it, preuaile with thoſe vngodly men? In ſtéede of <hi>honouring</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> their Parents, they <hi>diſhonour</hi> their Prince, and in their Prince their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> and their Countrey. In <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering,</hi> which is abhorred of all men, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> they offend moſt of all men. For <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie,</hi> they came to the height of <hi>Abſolons</hi> impietie, they committe it in the ſight of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> For <hi>ſtealing</hi> and <hi>theft,</hi> théeues robbe priuate men pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uily, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> but the Rebels and ſeditious, ſpoyle and burne many men, yea, the publike good of their Countrey, of the Church, of their Prince openly. If they who beare falſe witneſſe only againſt priuate men, breake the lawe, what doe the <hi>ſeditious,</hi> who by falſe rumours, flaunderous pretences, and manifeſt deceites, ſeeke to defame the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152155:17"/>
faithfull <hi>Counſellours,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſt. 16.13.14.</note> and moſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſeruants of their <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> that they being taken out of the way, they might lay wait for their Soueraigne: nay, who ſpare not their Soueraigne,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
but ſay vnto euery bold and vniuſt petitioner, <hi>See,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Sam. 1 5.3</note> 
                  <hi>thy matters are good and righteous, but there is no man depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the king to heare thee.</hi> But (to fill vp the meaſure of iniquitie) doth not this falſe witneſſe bearing againſt the Prince, procéede from vniuſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, deſires not lodging onely in their hearts, but breaking out at their <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> mouthes,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Oh that I were made iudge in the land, that euery man which hath any matter or controuerſie, might come to me?</hi> But is it <hi>O Abſolon, O Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.1.2 5.6.</note> is it (as thou pretendeſt) that thou mighteſt doe him iuſtice? wilt thou not when thy <hi>Charets</hi> and <hi>hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and many attendants, and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie, and popularitie, and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and diſſimulations, and kiſſing, hath ſtolen the hearts of the men of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> vnmaſke thy ſelfe? Thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeſt the place of a <hi>Iudge,</hi> to doe iuſtice to other, but thine owne <hi>ſpies</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:152155:18"/>
proclaime,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.10.</note> and thy trumpets ſound, that thou (<hi>200.</hi> in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by thee) aymeſt at the Crowne and Kingdome of thine owne father:<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.11.</note> he ſette thee vp, wilt thou pull him down? hee gaue thee life, wilt thou take away his life? he pardoned thy offence, wilt thou perſiſt in offending him,<note place="margin">Math. 5.9. Peacemaker, and peace-breaker, their difference, portion, and parentage. Horace.</note> and in offending God? <hi>peace-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> are <hi>bleſſed,</hi> becauſe they ſhall bee called the <hi>children</hi> of God: O <hi>peace-breaker</hi> thou art accurſed, thou muſt be accounted the <hi>ſonne</hi> of the Diuell. It is ſweete and comely to die for thy <hi>Countrey,</hi> wilt thou by <hi>Rebellion</hi> ſéek to bring thy Countrey to nought:<note place="margin">Math. 12.25. Ecclus. 16.7.</note> It was the impietie of the rebellious <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants</hi> to fight againſt God, but the ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious are guiltie of the <hi>Giants</hi> impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.2.</note> for, ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> hee that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God. If <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> when the <hi>Iewes</hi> braſt for anger, yet with this reaſon, leaſt they ſhould be found euen fighters againſt God,<note place="margin">Act. 5.33.34.38.39.</note> could cut of their conſultation to ſlay the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not the ſame reaſon bridle all the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous rancour of thy heart, who art in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152155:18"/>
                  <hi>name</hi> a Chriſtian, and therefore ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to haue crucified the fleſh,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.24.</note> with the affections and the luſts? But time not permitting me to ſpeake the leaſt part of that which might, and ſhould be ſaid of this daughter of Lucifer, know that this <hi>mother-vice</hi> breaketh out in <hi>Thought,</hi> in <hi>Word,</hi> and in <hi>Deed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shall not <hi>thought</hi> be free?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>God who is a ſpirit, will himſelfe be worſhipped in ſpirite and truth,<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.24.</note> and will haue ſeruants obedient to their maiſters, with feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, in ſingleneſſe of heart as vnto Chriſt, not with eye ſeruice as men pleaſers, but as the ſeruants of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.56. How we muſt ſeeue our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne. Gene. 6.5.</note> doing the will of God from the heart, will much more that ſubiects ſhall ſo ſerue their Soueraignes. Hee knoweth, the imagination of the thoughts of our heartes: and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth al imaginations of thoughts:<note place="margin">1. Chro. 28.9.</note> will haue an inquiſition made for the thoughts of the vngodly:<note place="margin">Wiſd. 1.9.</note> and if thou wilt not heare him, curſe not the king, no not in thy thought,<note place="margin">God both Wiſd. 20.1.3.</note> hee (from whome wicked thoughtes doe ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate) will haue it reuealed: for the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152155:19"/>
fowles of the heauen ſhall carrie the voice,<note place="margin">And threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealing of treacherous thoughts.</note> and that which hath wings ſhal declare the matter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How can the fowles of heauen carrie a voyce? how can that which hath winges declare it? or any man diſcouer the thoughts of our hearts?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Examples of ſecret ſinnes reuealed. Acts. 5.2.3. Dan. 13.45, 46, 54.58. 2. Pet. 2.26.</note>Hee who ſhewed to Saint <hi>Peter</hi> the ſecrete compact of <hi>Ananias,</hi> and <hi>Saphira;</hi> he who raiſed vp the holy ſpirit of a yong childe to cleare <hi>Suſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and conuict the wicked Iudges: he who cauſed the dumbe Aſſe ſpeaking with mans voyce, to forbid the fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Prohhet: he who diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Beſſus</hi> his Paracide by the chatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rtng of Swallowes:<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> he can cauſe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie foule of heauen, and euerie creature vpon the earth, to reueale and reuenge our mutinous,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 5.17, 20</note> flaunderous, ſedicious, and impious thoughts againſt <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>To him that hath not denied the power of godlineſſe, it is inough, that God hath forbid vs to curſe the king in our thought: to euerie beleeuer it is inough, that God hath foretold the declaring of ſuch thoughts: to euery one that is not an open Infidell it is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152155:19"/>
inough, that he neede not go farre for an informer, If they with <hi>Michal</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe <hi>Dauid</hi> in their heerts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Michals thought vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by her owne tongue</note> 
                  <hi>their owne tongues ſometimes with <hi>Michals</hi> vtter it, O how glorious was the king of <hi>Iſrael</hi> this day, which was vncoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to day in the eyes of the May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of his ſeruants, as a foole vncoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth himſelfe: and with her,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">And puniſhed by Gods hand 2. Sam. 6.20.23.</note> 
                  <hi>for this crime, receiue puniſhment at the handes of God. Therefore <hi>Michal</hi> the daughter of <hi>Saul</hi> had no child vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the day of her death. Yet pardon mee though I deſire to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans law forbid euill thoughts of <hi>Caeſar?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>The lawes of men for <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon crimes</hi> puniſh onely <hi>wordes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Both the ciuil and common law puniſh treacherous thoughts with death. 13. Eliz. 1.</note> and <hi>deedes:</hi> but for this point of high <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> if any man hath thought it, though hee neuer attempted it, the lawe both Ciuill and Common, doth puniſh him with death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne:</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But was there euer ſuch a preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſeene?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The law in this point, when &amp; where executed.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>Neither farre hence, nor long ſince, neede we looke for ſuch a preſident. That <hi>Norman</hi> Gentleman
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152155:20"/>
who confeſſed to a <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Frier, that he had a thought to kil <hi>Frances</hi> the firſt of <hi>France,</hi> though he had changed his minde, repented, and aſked pardon of that crime, yet the Frier reporting it to the King, and the King referring it to the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> the graue court of that great Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, though that king ſhewed himſelfe very graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, condemned him to death. Yea ſo great deteſtation is there to bee had of the leaſt ſhew of violence to the prince, that whereas the law excuſeth madde men from puniſhment:<note place="margin">Madneſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth not the ſhew of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to the Prince.</note> (madneſſe it ſelfe being ſo great a puniſhment) yet when <hi>Capito,</hi> a man raging mad, drew his ſworde vpon <hi>Henrie,</hi> the ſonne of king <hi>Frances,</hi> hee was therefore exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Since to offend <hi>Caeſar</hi> euen in the thoughts of my heart, it is prohibited and puniſhed both by God and man: how may my heart be preſerued from wicked thoughts againſt <hi>Caeſar?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The cuſtodie of the heart is the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of the tongue, and whole bodie.</note>As hee that woulde haue a ſtreame ſweet &amp; wholſome, wil haue care that the ſpring bee kept from poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and all corruption: ſo, if thou wilt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152155:20"/>
haue the words of thy tongue, and the works of thy hande, to ſauour nothing but pure alleagiance, then muſt thou of neceſſitie, firſt ſee that the thoughts of thy heart bee pure from this vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous infection.<note place="margin">
                     <p>That thy thoughts may be pure from al corruption, thy heartmuſt bee puryfied, and kept. Purifying of the heart ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>Gen. 8.21. daungerous polution, 1 Cor. 5.6. and a fearefull Wiſdom. 1.4. aſſertion. Ieremie. 4.14. What purify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our harts. Iames. 2.19. Acts. 15.9. and how. Reuel. 1.5.</p>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How is that done?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>By purifying thy heart. By kéeping thy heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Needeth my heart purifying?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>In regard of the originall corruption, in regard of the dangerous polution, in regard of a fearefull aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I ſay with <hi>Ieremie:</hi> O <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe, that thou mayeſt be ſaued: how longe ſhall thy wicked thoughtes remaine within thée?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that gift of God which purifyeth our hearts?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faith</hi> (not euerie Faith for the Diuels alſo beléeue and tremble) Faith puryfieth the heartes, for being the hand of the ſoule, it apprehendeth &amp; applyeth vnto vs Ieſus Chriſt, who hath waſhed vs from our ſinnes in his bloud.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What helpes bee there for the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152155:21"/>
confirmation of our Faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Helpes hereof bee</note> 
                  <hi>and purify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our hearts?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prayer,</hi> the <hi>word,</hi> the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prayer, Pſa. 51.20.</note> Prayer, and therefore pray with <hi>Dauid, Create in me a cleane hart O God, and renew a right ſpirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 15.3. The word.</note> The word, <hi>Now,</hi> ſayth Chriſt, <hi>are ye cleane through the word which I haue ſpoken vnto you.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 1.23.25. The word as a glaſſe.</note> The word hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth to purifie as <hi>water,</hi> it helpeth to purifie as a <hi>glaſſe,</hi> as a glaſſe it ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our corruptions, as water it ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to waſh away our corruptions.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 13.14. As water hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth to purify the heart. The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. 1. Mac. 6.34. The heart 1. Cor. 6.19. of a chriſtian, the holy of holyes. Hence Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie 16. in vs.</note>Sacraments, <hi>ſhewing the Lordes death till he come,</hi> as the bloud of Grapes and Mulberies prouoked the Elephants to fight, purifie our hearts, and prouoke vs to fight againſt all corruptions that can come.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Muſt wee bee verie carefull of this?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>If thy body be the Temple of the holy Ghoſt, then muſt thy heart bee <hi>Sanctum ſanctorum,</hi> the holy of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes. Hence good in thée, if the roote be holy, ſo are the braunches: if thy heart be cleane, ſo will thy tongue, ſo will thy handes. Hence fauours on earth,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152155:21"/>
hee that loueth pureneſſe of heart,<note place="margin">Fauours on earth. Prou. 22.11.</note> 
                  <hi>for the grace of his lippes, the Kinge ſhalbe his friend.</hi> Hence glorie in Heauen,<note place="margin">Math. 5.8. Felicitie in Heauen.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>So hath this of the puryfying of the heart, rauiſhed my heart, that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire for the keeping of my heart, to be alſo inſtructed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>For this heare <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Keeping of the heart. Prou. 4.23.</note> kéepe thy heart with all diligence. And firſt of all, ſince as except the Lord kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the Citie,<note place="margin">pſ. 127.1.</note> the Kéeper watcheth it in vaine: ſo vnleſſe the Lorde kéepeth the Cittie of thy heart, thou kéepeſt it in vaine. As the Prieſts with hands lift vp to Heauen, beſought him that was euer the defendour of their Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the Temple,<note place="margin">2. Mac. 14.34, 36.</note> with lift vp hands and bowed knées,<note place="margin">For keeping thy heart pray to God.</note> beſéech the preſeruer of thy ſoule, <hi>O moſte holy Lord keepe this houſe (of my heart) euer vndefiled which lately was clenſed:</hi> praying to God to kéepe it, Libertine-like, be not thou then ſecure, (If <hi>Lucifer</hi> in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, if <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradice,<note place="margin">preſume not.</note> if <hi>Iudas</hi> in the Schoole of Chriſt fell, what place can there bee for carnall ſecuritie?
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152155:22"/>
Bleſſed is the man, ſayth the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">prou. 28.14. But vſe dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</note> that feareth alway) But ſayth <hi>Salomon,</hi> kéepe thy heart, kéepe thy heart with diligence, kéepe thy heart with all diligence: with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence within, leaſt there ariſe corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from within thy heart: with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence without, leaſt from without there come corruption into thy heart: within,<note place="margin">Within.</note> leaſt corruption ariſe within, for euen as in a wéeded Garden, there will ſpring vp newe wéedes, ſo, euen in the puryfied heart, ſince there is ſtill ſinne dwelling,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.20. Rom. 6.12. Becauſe of ſin dwelling. 2. Sam. 3.1. Gal. 5.17.</note> though not ſin raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as there was a long time warre betwéene the houſe of <hi>Saule,</hi> and the houſe of <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſo there will be a longe time ſtriuing betwéen the fleſh and the ſpirite,<note place="margin">Ouid. The poets ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</note> as the Poet aduiſeth ſtop the beginning: for as it was ſaid of <hi>Babell,</hi> ſo of the fleſh (whoſe luſts cheriſhed, will be our <hi>Babell,</hi> our Confuſion) may it moſt fitly be ſayd,<note place="margin">pſal. 137.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed ſhall he be that taketh and daſheth thy young ones againſt the ſtones.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 12.29, 31.</note> When the firſt born of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was ſlaine, Iſraell was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered: when the firſt temptation is cut off, we are freed: kéepe thy heart
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152155:22"/>
with diligence from without,<note place="margin">And without becauſe of the Diuell temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Eph. 2.2.</note> for as <hi>Abner</hi> ſtrenthened the houſe of <hi>Saule,</hi> ſo the Prince of darkneſſe, that ruleth in the ayre, euen the ſpirite that nowe worketh in the Children of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſtrengthneth the fleſh againſt the ſpirit, the affections againſt reaſon, he being the firſt Rebell dayly inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to Rebellion. But <hi>reſiſt him</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Iames, and he ſhall fly from thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Whome if we reſiſt hee will flie. Iames. 4.7. From whom ſeducers to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition bee ſent.</note> If any <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> (ſuch be your ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Libellers, lewd Inuentors of fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſightes, and prodigious appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and others of like braine) be ſent out by this ſpirituall <hi>Senacherib,</hi> to drawe either you from Alleagiance to <hi>Hezechiah,</hi> or <hi>Hezechiah</hi> from confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the Lord (ſince they that are ſuch ſerue not the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.18. Whom they ſerue, and what they do. Rom. 16.17. Howe.</note> but their owne bellies, and with faire ſpéech and flattering deceaue the harts of the ſimple) I beſéech all Subiects, that they would marke ſuch and auoid them: nay, ſince ſuch ſerue not the Lord Ieſus Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (who commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs to giue to <hi>Caeſar</hi> thoſe thinges that are <hi>Caeſars,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 22.21.</note> who ſubmitted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to <hi>Caeſars</hi> Lieuetenant)<note place="margin">Iohn. 19.11.</note> but neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152155:23"/>
his example, and tranſgreſſe his Commandement, and not his alone, but reſiſt the ordinance of his father,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.2.</note> I charge thee my ſonne, though thy hand bee not preſently vpon them, as it was commaunded againſt them that ſought to ſeduce to Idolatrie,<note place="margin">Deut. 13.6.</note> yet though it bee a Prophet that giueth a ſigne or a wonder, the Sonne of thy mother,<note place="margin">They are to be</note> or thine owne Sonne, or thy Daughter, or thy Wife, that lyeth in thy boſome, or thy friende, who is as thine owne ſoule, entice thee ſecretly, thou ſhalt not conſent vnto him, nor heare him, neither ſhal thine eye pitty him, ſhew mercy, nor kéep him ſecret. <hi>Nulla eſt excuſatio peccati,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cicero in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aelius.</note> 
                  <hi>ſi amici cauſa peccaueris,</hi> It is no excuſe of thy of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, that for thy friendes ſake thou diddeſt offend. But (not to ſpeake ſo hard in this crime as in that) diſcouer him or her,<note place="margin">Entertained, and wherfore. Againſt them we are to watch.</note> how neere, how deere ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, to ſhew thy true loyaltie to <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> thy religious dutie to thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. And as <hi>Ionathan</hi> in regard of the enemies, commanded his men to watch,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.13. Arme.</note> &amp; to be in armes ready to fight, ſo kéepe thy ſoule diligently, and bee
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152155:23"/>
armed for reſiſtance. And as <hi>Ioachim</hi> vpon the comming of <hi>Holofernes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudith. 4.6.7.</note> wrote to the <hi>Bethulians,</hi> to keepe the paſſages of the Mountaines, for by them there was an entrie into <hi>Iudea:</hi> ſo keepe the paſſages of thy ſences,<note place="margin">Keepe our ſences.</note> for by them there is an entrie into thy heart. Wee reſiſt an enemie rather without the <hi>gates,</hi> than within the <hi>walles:</hi> ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> that his heart might not fall into vanitie,<note place="margin">Pſa. 119.37.</note> prayed to God to turne away his eyes, that he might not behold vanitie,<note place="margin">Iob. 31.1.</note> and to this ende did <hi>Iob</hi> make a couenant with his eyes.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.33.</note> If euill words (written or ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken) corrupt good manners, with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> pray, that God would turne away thy eyes and thy eares: with <hi>Iob</hi> make a couenant with thy eyes, and with thy eares, that they looke not on, that they heare not any kind of ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Libelles, trecherous pamphlets,<note place="margin">Prou. 24.21. Where we be to arme moſt.</note> or the ſmootheſt wordes tending to Rebellion. My ſonne, ſayth <hi>Salomon,</hi> meddle not with them that are ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Arme moſt where thou art wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt, for where thou art weakeſt, there will they aſſault moſt. Is Indian
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152155:24"/>
gold offered to make battery in an Engliſh heart;<note place="margin">How againſt couetouſnes. 1. Tim. 6.10.</note> with both thy eares receiue that Oracle, <hi>The loue of mony is the roote of all euill:</hi> with both thy eyes beholde <hi>Iudas,</hi> who for loue of money betrayed his Maſter.<note place="margin">Math. 27.5. Howe againſt ambition. Iudg. 9.14.</note> Art thou high minded? doe the ſeditious ſay to thee, as the trees did vnto the bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>Come thou and raigne ouer vs.</hi> Remember that God reſiſteth the proude.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.5. Eſa. 14.12.</note> How art thou fallen from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen O <hi>Lucifer,</hi> ſonne of the morning? Art thou wrathfull? doe they enflame thée with reuenge? remember, the wrath of man doth not accompliſh the righteouſneſſe of God:<note place="margin">Iames 1.20. How againſt wrath. Rom. 12.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Mihi vindicta,</hi> auenge not your ſelues, <hi>Vengeance is mine, I will repay, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member a fathers curſe vpon his two ſonnes, that were brethren in euill; <hi>Curſed bee their wrath,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 49.7.</note> 
                  <hi>for it was fierce, and their rage, for it was cruell, I will diuide them in <hi>Iacob,</hi> and ſcatter them in Iſrael.</hi> Remember that of Chriſt, <hi>So likewiſe ſhall myne heauenly Father doe vnto you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 18 35.</note> 
                  <hi>except ye forgiue from your hearts, each one to his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their treſpaſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:152155:24"/>If euer thou haſt in thought offended, that which <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Simon Magus</hi> for his <hi>Simoniacall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aduice to all Acts 8, 22. Who haue offended in diſloyall thoughts.</note> I to thée for thy <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall</hi> intent, do ſay, <hi>Repent of this thy wickedneſſe, and pray God, that if it bee poſſible, the thought of thy heart may be forgiuen thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your inſtruction for the thoughts of my heart finiſhed, my next ſuit is, that you would next giue me inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the words of my tongue.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>Seditious thoughts like an inwarde maladie,<note place="margin">Seditious words worſe then ſeditious thoughts.</note> bee hurtfull to the heart, wherein they reſt, therfore are they to bee auoyded: but ſeditious words like a contagious diſeaſe do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect others, therefore are they more to be abhorred. But if thy heart be good, thy ſpéech ſaith <hi>Socrates,</hi> wil ſhew like a Temple excellent ſimilitudes of thy ſoule, as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Out of the good treaſure of thy hart thou wilt bring forth good things.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 12 35.</note> If at the preſence of <hi>Iob</hi> (who was as a king in the land of <hi>Hus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 29.10.</note> and his friends as Princes) the voice of Princes was hid, and their tongue cleaued to the roofe of their mouth, ſhal the voyces of meane perſons breake
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152155:25"/>
out againſt their <hi>Caeſar?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Examples of reuerence in ſpeech. 1. pet. 3.6. Gen 31.35. Act. 26.24, 25</note> If <hi>Sara</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to her huſbande <hi>Abraham,</hi> gaue him the title of <hi>ſir:</hi> If <hi>Rachel</hi> ſpeaking to her father <hi>Laban,</hi> called him <hi>Lord:</hi> If Saint <hi>Paul</hi> conuented before a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan <hi>Preſident,</hi> and told by him, that too much learning made him mad, reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>O noble <hi>Feſtus;</hi>
                  </hi> if to king <hi>Agrippa,</hi> he for honor ſake (in that ſix and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Chapter) be found ſix times to haue giuen the title of <hi>King,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iames. 1.19. The Canon of the Apoſtles Natures work manſhip. Dauids reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. Pſal. 39.1. Iames. 3.9. The end of the tongue. The reward of him that vſeth it well Ecclus. 21.28. Our proaneſſe to fall by it. Iames. 3.2. Ecclus. 14.1. The difficulty of reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it.</note> who can ſpeake of ſo high maieſtie, without giuing thereto <hi>honour?</hi> If I call to mind how Saint <hi>Iames</hi> hath willed euery man to be ſlow to ſpeake; If I conſider how nature hath compaſſed my tongue with a double ante-mure, one of my lippes, another of my teeth; If <hi>Dauids</hi> reſolution, <hi>I will take heed to my waies, that I ſin not with my tongue;</hi> If the end of this member, to bleſſe God: the reward of him that well vſeth it: <hi>Hee that keepeth his tongue, and is diſcreete, ſhall come to honour:</hi> our proanneſſe to fall by it; he that falleth not in this, Saint <hi>Iames</hi> calleth him a <hi>perfect,</hi> and the Sonne of <hi>Sirac, a bleſſed</hi> man: the difficultie of reclaiming it, <hi>the whole
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152155:25"/>
nature of birds, and of beaſts, and of cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thinges,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iames. 3.7.8. The Treaſure which he kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, that kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth it. Prou. 13.3. Eſay. 6.6, 7. The Author (of the euill tongue.) Iames. 3.6. The ſcituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Ibidem. The damage which it doth Iames. 3.5. The name thereof not a Rod. Pſal. 57.4, A ſharp ſword Ecclus. 28.17. Iames. 3.6. Fire.</note> 
                  <hi>and thinges of the ſea is tamed; and hath beene tamed of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man, but the tongue can no man tame: it is an vnruly euill,</hi> what he kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth that kéepeth it, <hi>he that keepeth his mouth, keepeth his life;</hi> the Author not as the Prophets by a bleſſed <hi>Seraphin</hi> with a coale from the Aulter of God, but by the wicked ſpirit, <hi>It is ſet on fire of hell:</hi> For the ſcituation, <hi>ſo is the tong ſet among the members, that it defileth the whole body:</hi> the hurt which it doth, behold, howe great a thing a little fire kindleth: Shall I call it a Rod? An euill tongue is called a ſharpe ſword, not a Rod, for the ſtroake of the rodde maketh markes in the fleſh, but the ſtroke of the tongue breaketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bones; but becauſe the ſword cutteth no more then at once it toucheth, the Apoſtle calleth it fire, which goeth on further ſtill burning and conſuming. The <hi>pſalmiſt</hi> a poyſon, Adders poyſon,<note place="margin">Pſal. 140.3. Adders poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Iames. 3.8.</note> the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> full of deadly poyſon, which goeth on ſtill further infecting and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenoming, but poiſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enuenometh not, fire conſumeth not, but thinges néere
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152155:26"/>
hand that they touch, but the tongue back-biteth him that is farre abſent from vs,<note place="margin">Ieremie. 9.8.</note> and therefore <hi>Ieremie</hi> calleth it an <hi>Arrowe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">An arrowe ſhot out.</note> not an arrow in the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, for then it would not hurt: but an arrow ſhot out,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 1.22.</note> and ſo it will ſlay. The Bow of <hi>Ionathan</hi> neuer turned backe,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2 2.9, 10, 18, 19.</note> ſome tongues be ſo bent as they will neuer turne backe: the bowe or arrowe of <hi>Ionathan</hi> kils one at a ſhot, but the tongue of <hi>Doeg,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 51.3.</note> at a ſhotte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides women, Children, Sucklinges, Oxes,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.7.</note> Aſſes, and ſhéepe, killed 85 per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that were a <hi>linnen Ephod.</hi> The Archers of the Philiſtines wounded <hi>Saule,</hi> but becauſe they were enemies: but the tongue of <hi>Shimei</hi> wounded <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> the one being a Soueraigne, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Subiect. <hi>Shimeis</hi> tongue woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Dauid</hi> when hee was abroad, flée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wéeping, his head couered, his féet bare, his people about him mourning, his enemie raigning: but is there any tongue that will, that dare, that can wound <hi>Dauid</hi> being within the priuie Chamber of his owne Court; tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing, bleſſing God for deliueries, his head crowned, his féet of all true harts
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152155:26"/>
honoured, all true Subiects reioycing and giuing thankes to God, who bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>Dauid,</hi> and them in <hi>Dauid,</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies at home &amp; abroad, by the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prouidence and mightie hand of the Lord, detected and confounded? Is there, ſuch a tongue, is there ſuch a tongue in all Iſraell? Is there ſuch a tongue in all England? that tongue is neither Rod, nor ſword, nor poyſon,<note place="margin">A ſeditious tongue no Rod no ſword no poyſon, no fire.</note> nor fire, nor arrowe, nor arrow ſhotte out, nor arrow of <hi>Ionathan,</hi> nor arrow of the Philiſtines, nor ſhotte of <hi>Doeg,</hi> nor tongue of <hi>Shimei,</hi> (whome neither holy <hi>Dauid</hi> dying, nor wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> raigning, thought méete to bee pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) but hell it ſelfe: Nay,<note place="margin">But Hell it ſelfe. Eccus. 28.21.</note> heare not me, heare Ieſus the Sonne of <hi>Sirac: Hell</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>were better then ſuch a one.</hi> Hath any man ſuch a tongue, and yet goeth for a Chriſtian? and yet ſéemeth to be religious?<note place="margin">The ſeditious tongue doth but counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Religion. Iames. 1.26. The badde tongue worſe then a theefe.</note> Let him heare <hi>S. Iames: If any man among you ſeemeth religious, and refraineth not his tongue, but deceiueth his owne heart, this mans Religion is vaine.</hi> Oh howe wicked then is a had tongue? how wicked be Theeues? but Theeues (ſayth Saint
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152155:27"/>
                  <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) be more tollerable then the badde tongue. Théeues take away our riches, but a badde tongue taketh away out good name, which in the iudgement of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 22.1. Iohn 1.34.</note> is to be choſen aboue great riches. O cruell ſpeare of the ſouldiour, which pierced the ſide of my Sauiour: O cruell tongue of the Seditious,<note place="margin">The ſeditious tongue Prou. 25.3.</note> which (though <hi>Salomon</hi> affirmeth, that the heauens in height, &amp; the earth in déepnes, &amp; the kings hart can no man ſearch out) pierceth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head and heart of my ſoueraigne. The ſpeare of the Souldier pierced not the ſide of my Sauiour,<note place="margin">Compared to the ſouldiers ſpeare Iohn 19.33 34.</note> vntill hee was dead, the tongue of the ſeditious, (I tremble to thinke of it) pierceth the head and heart of my Soueraigne in her life. There is not (ſayde the ſonne of <hi>Sirac) a more wicked head,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecclus 25.17.</note> 
                  <hi>then the head of a ſerpent,</hi> yet is the tong of the ſeditious head as wicked, as the head of a Serpent,<note place="margin">
                     <p>The ſeditious tongue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</p>
                     <p>The ſeditious tongue as euil as the head of a ſerpent.</p>
                  </note> the tongue of the ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious head, is more wicked then the head of a Serpent. Is as wicked as the head of a ſerpent, the Serpent is trecherous, it ſtingeth in ſecret, the tongue of the ſeditious is trecherous,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152155:27"/>
it ſtingeth in ſecret; at the voyce of a man the Serpent flyeth, at the voyce of a good Subiect the ſeditious is ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent; the Serpent feedeth but vpon the duſt of the earth, the ſeditious tongue talketh but of the infirmities that bee, nay lewdly faineth infirmities to be in the Prince: the Serpent goeth not ſtraight along, but wreatheth and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolueth himſelfe, the ſeditious ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not ſincerely and plainly, but wil proteſt that he is ſorie to ſée this, ſorie to heare that, he, forſooth, wiſheth one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſauing of ſoules, and the good of the eſtate; and yet he is more wicked then the head of a Serpent,<note place="margin">The ſeditious tongue worſe then the head of a ſerpent.</note> The Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent poyſoneth one at once, but the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill tongue (Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayth) poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoneth thrée at once, himſelfe that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, him that he ſpeaketh of, and him that he ſpeaketh too; but (there) reſteth not his poyſon, for at the ſame inſtant he offendeth God,<note place="margin">Acts. 10.33,</note> in whoſe preſence we all do ſpeake. And therefore if you will know how wicked he is, God by S. <hi>Iames</hi> telleth vs, that the tongue is not wicked, but wickedneſſe, not a little, but a great wickedneſſe, And if
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152155:28"/>
you woulde knowe howe great,<note place="margin">The euil tong Iames 3.6. A worlde of wickedneſſe. Gen. 9.22.25. Examples which may moue vs to take heede to our tongue. Numb. 12.10. 2. Sam. 6.7.</note> hee ſayth it is a world of wickedneſſe. If <hi>Cham</hi> (who told his brethren of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers nakednes) had that ſentence fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his father, <hi>Curſed be Canaan, a ſeruant of ſeruants ſhall he be to his brethren:</hi> If <hi>Miriam</hi> (though a Propheteſſe) mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring agaynſt <hi>Moyſes</hi> the leader of Iſrael was leprous like ſnow: If <hi>Vz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zah</hi> for putting his hande to the Arke of God, incurred Gods ſo great indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that he ſtroke him in the place, that hee died in the place: what may he looke for at the handes of God, who ſhal ſet his mouth againſt heauen, and bend his tongue againſt the God vpon earth?<note place="margin">Pray for the gouernment of the tong. Pſal. 141.3. Murmur not ſaith Paul. Phil, 2.14.</note> when thou ſhouldeſt not ſpeake, make a doore, and a barre, and a ſure bridle for thy mouth: pray with <hi>Dauid: Set a watch (O Lord) before my mouth, and keepe the doore of lippes:</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that of <hi>Paul, Do all things without murmuring, and reaſonings:</hi> That of God himſelfe, <hi>Thou ſhalt not walke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with tales among thy people:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sow not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Leuit. 16.16. Saith God himſelfe.</note> Nay ſince ſuch are fitte to kindle the fire of ſedition, and their wordes ſinke déepe, thou muſt driue them away with thine
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152155:28"/>
angrie countenance, yea, I cannot but ſay with the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Prou. 25.23. Frowne vpon ſuch ſayth Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon. Wiſh them cut off with the Apoſtle.</note> 
                  <hi>wold to God they were euen cut off which doe diſquiet you.</hi> when of thy Soueraigne, to whom (as <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſayd to his Sonne) God ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to haue ſayd, <hi>Curſed be he that curſeth thee, and bleſſed be he that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thee,</hi> thou ſhalt ſpeake, Pray al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Whome god ſeemeth to bleſſe, and Gen. 27.29. whome to curſe. Pſal. 51.15. Pray forthy ſpeech of thy Soueraigne.</note> 
                  <hi>Open thou my lippes O Lord, and my mouth ſhall ſhewe forth thy praiſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Since neither in <hi>Thought,</hi> nor in <hi>Word,</hi> much leſſe in <hi>Action,</hi> may I breake my Alleagiance to <hi>Caeſar:</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>Much leſſe, my Sonne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But muſt I then obey an hard and oppreſſing Prince?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>Were he as cruell as <hi>Holo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernes,</hi> thou wert to obey him. If thou haddeſt alreadie played the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitiue,<note place="margin">Iudith. 3.7, 8. Allegiance muſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed to the hardeſt Prince. Puniſhments of Fugitiues. Counſaile for Fugitiues.</note> (a Fugitiue the <hi>Aeginians</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with the loſſe of the Thumbe of the right hande, the <hi>Samians</hi> with the picture of an Owle branded in their face, the <hi>Mitylenians</hi> with the loſſe of their liues) and wert now in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemies Troupes, Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the <hi>Mandate,</hi> not of a man of <hi>Beli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:152155:29"/>
but of an Angell of the Lord, to <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> lately fled from <hi>Sara,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 16.6, 9.</note> who had dealt roughly with her, <hi>return vnto thy Dame and humble thy ſelfe vnder her handes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But what if he be a wicked and vngodly Prince?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nabuchodonozor</hi> was ſo, and yet was <hi>Zedechiah</hi> gréeuouſly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed,<note place="margin">Allegiance muſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to the vngodly Prince.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſacked, Iſraell miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably afflicted for rebelling againſt him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But what if the vngodly Prince commaund mee to doe that which is wicked and vngodly?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 17. 2. Tim. 3.6. Iude. 19. Math. 23.15. 2. Peter. 1.20. Pſ. 119.105. The vngodly Prince is not to be obayed in vngodlines Acts. 5.29. But beware thou ſpeakeſt not euill of God, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt not ſweet Sowe.</note>Firſt be ſure that thou béeſt not miſ-led either by theſe whom <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Iude</hi> deſcribe, nor by ſuch to whom Chriſt himſelfe doth denounce a woe, and then being aſſured of this, by the conſtant Harmonie, not priuate inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of that which thou oughteſt to account <hi>a Lanterne vnto thy feet, and a light vnto thy pathes,</hi> Reſolue with Saint <hi>Peter, wee ought rather to obey God then men.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But if a man adorned with ſinguler vertues, honoured of the people, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in the Court, great in authoritie,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152155:29"/>
deſeruing well of Prince and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, beeing oppreſſed by a wicked king, the king though there bee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt teſtimonie of moſt aſſured loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie, ſtill perſecuting him, may he not by his Princes perill, free himſelf from perill?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>Either neuer purified, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill kept hath thy heart beene, who once durſt think, much more propound ſuch a queſtion. The <hi>Eſſei,</hi> the wiſeſt, and moſt vertuous Sect among the Iewes,<note place="margin">Ioſephus.</note> affirme that the perſon of the Prince, is of the Subiects to be accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>ſacred:</hi> the Ciuilians teach, that it is ſacriledge to diſpute of that which is done by the Prince, and dare anie diſpute whether any man for any cauſe may offer ſo vnſpeakeable out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to that ſacred perſon?<note place="margin">Aduice to the yong, yet fit for all. Not Sauls wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kedneſſe, not Dauids deſerts nor any other motiue could ſeduce Dauid to indaunger Saul.</note> Vpon my bleſſing, let not thy heart euer hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter entertaine ſuch a thought, nor thy eare heare, much leſſe thy tongue ſpeake ſuch a worde. Yet for this time let thy ſelfe, &amp; all with thy ſelfe, learne of <hi>Dauid,</hi> a man according to Gods owne heart. To whom better might it be done then to <hi>Saule,</hi> for who wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152155:30"/>
then <hi>Saule? Saule</hi> wicked to God, whoſe expreſſe commandement by tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the pray he tranſgreſſed.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.3.19.9. verſ.</note> Not ſecret and hidden was his wickednes, but open and apparant,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.26.27.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Samuel</hi> ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reprooued him, God reiected him, and by a manifeſt ſigne ſhewed hee had reiected him,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 16.14.</note> an euill ſpirit ſent of the Lord vexed him. who might do it better then <hi>Dauid? Dauid</hi> deſerued well of the people and Countrey, by ſlaying <hi>Goliah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.24.50.51.</note> the Philiſtine, the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the whole Countrey, deſerued well of <hi>Saul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 19.5.</note> not onely for this publike ſeruice to him, and his Countrey, but alſo for that other priuate,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 16.23.</note> in eaſing him of the euill ſpirite. Who better then <hi>Dauid?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18.5.</note> hee was accepted in the ſight of <hi>Saules</hi> ſeruants, all <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> loued him,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 18.7.</note> the verie women ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured him with <hi>Tenne Thouſand</hi> for <hi>Saules one Thouſand. Dauid</hi> no ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie ſubiect, <hi>Dauid</hi> was ſet ouer the men of warre, went in and out before the men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> fought the Lords Battailes,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 18.27.</note> was the Kings ſonne in law, was annoynted King by <hi>Samuel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 16.12.</note> at the commandement of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152155:30"/>
God himſelfe. And how was <hi>Dauid</hi> prouoked? not his wife alone ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken awaye, but his life ſought: not in woorde, but in déede: not by ſome flight blow to giue him a ſcarre, but by a mortall wound to take away his life: and this by no enemie, but by his owne Soueraigne, by his owne Father in law, By his owne Soue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raigne, by his owne Father in lawe, whome his owne hand ſaued from the open enemie, eaſed from the euill ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, not by the bribed, or enforced ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of ſo baſe. Cut-throat, but by the violence of the Kings owne hand, Not in a Fray in the field, but by the throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a ſpeare, when he was playing on the Harpe to eaſe <hi>Saule</hi> of the euill ſpirit. In perill he put him not once,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 18.10.11.</note> in perill he put him often: his former ſeruice was forgot, the mediation of a Sonne, for a Sonne in lawe to a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, would not ſerue: the ſlaughter of the innocent Prieſts would not ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his bloudie minde:<note place="margin">1 Sam. 20.32, 33.</note> the time of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence (though time deuoreth al things) coulde not aſwage his furie, his furie being ſo great, that <hi>Dauids</hi> ſauing of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152155:31"/>
his life,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 24.5, 7.</note> when he had him in the Caue, coulde not quench the flame of it, but his bloud ſpared by <hi>Dauid,</hi> he ſtill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth to ſeeke the bloud of <hi>Dauid:</hi> ſo that he liuing <hi>Dauid</hi> was ſtill in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to die, hee dead, in all apparence <hi>Dauid</hi> was ſure to raigne: hee was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine cloſed into <hi>Dauids</hi> hand, <hi>Dauid</hi> néede not touch him,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 26.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Abiſhai</hi> deſires but leaue that hee might ſmite him, ſnite him hee would but once to make him ſure: not any mans bloud but his alone néed be ſhed, that this was done either in his preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or by his conſent,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.7.</note> who could make report ſince this was in the night? and that it might ſéeme that God himſelfe fauored him in this Action,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.12.</note> God ſent a dead ſleepe vppon them. If then thou wilt know <hi>Dauids</hi> minde in this matter, from his owne mouth heare his <hi>prohibition,</hi> his <hi>reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.9, 10, 11. His prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> his <hi>queſtion,</hi> and his <hi>prayer.</hi> his prohibition, <hi>Dauid</hi> will not onely not act it, but hee will not permit it: and therefore to <hi>Abiſhais</hi> offered ſeruice, there is this charge returned,<note place="margin">Verſe. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Deſtroy him not.</hi> Queſtion, if <hi>Abiſhai</hi> ſhould take this for an ouer-ſight,<note place="margin">His Queſtion.</note> here is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152155:31"/>
to ſatiſfie him: <hi>Who can lay his hand on the Lords annoynted,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibidem,</note> 
                  <hi>and bee guiltleſſe?</hi> No man ſo good, no Prince ſo bad, no cauſe ſo great, that can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with violence offred to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords annoynted. His reſolution teſtified by an oath, not by the <hi>mercie</hi> of God, which the deſperate feele not, nor the <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of God, which the Libertine feareth not, nor the prouidence of God, whervpon moſt wicked men relie not, nor the <hi>Omni-preſence</hi> of God, which the offenders remember not, but by the <hi>life</hi> of God, which the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens aboue vs, ſetting forth his glorie,<note place="margin">Pſa. 19.1.</note> the ayre about vs, dayly infected, and dayly purified, the ſea aſide vs, at his commaundement ſtaying her proude waues, the earth beneath vs,<note place="margin">Iob. 38.11.</note> ſo huge a maſſe firmely fixed in the midſt of the ayre, our ſoules and our ſelues (for wee are his generation) doe proclaime,<note place="margin">Acts 17.28.</note> by this life of God, doth he teſtifie his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 26.10.</note> that where many thirſt for reuenge, <hi>Dauid</hi> will take no reuenge, whereas many wicked children bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ks of the father for a little wealth, <hi>Dauid</hi> woulde not the death of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152155:32"/>
in lawe for the Crowne. Many a man hath taken armes againſt his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne for his owne ſafetie: for his owne ſafetie, <hi>Dauid</hi> will not aſſaile his Soueraigne, but taking Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for his ſhéeld, vſing praier for ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour (ſaying in heart with Chriſt, <hi>Shall I not drinke of the cup that my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath giuen me</hi>) faith, <hi>the Lord ſhal ſmite him, or his day ſhal come to dy, or he ſhall diſcend into battaile &amp; periſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> His prayer, (the Lord knoweth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ine infirmities, leaſt iniurie mooue mee, ambition puffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mee, his inflexibilitie driue: mee, my owne ſafetie drawes mee, oportunitie intice t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mee, fonde fréends incenſe me) <hi>the Lord keepe me from laying mine hand vpon the Lordes annoynted.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 18.11, Sam. 26.10. His reſolution 1. Sam. 26.11 His Inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 2 Sam. 1.10.</note> Will yet any man doe its here ye, heare what he ſaid to <hi>Abiſhai</hi> hereafter ſée what he did to the <hi>Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kite,</hi> though the <hi>Amalekite</hi> brought him the Crowne from <hi>Saule</hi> his head, and the Braflet from his arme: After he had not clapt his handes for <hi>ioy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.11.12</note> but rent his cloathes for <hi>greefe,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee had not reioiced and laughed, but mourned and lamented, after he
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152155:32"/>
had not <hi>feaſted</hi> but <hi>faſted;</hi> (mindfull of that in the Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 105.15. 2. Sam. 1.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Touch not mine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed</hi>) he ſaith, <hi>How waſt thou not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to put foorth thine hand to deſtroy the anoynted of the Lord?</hi> To kill a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man it is death, to kill a Prince it is more then death: to kill a man is death, becauſe he is the Image of God:<note place="margin">Gen. 9.6.</note> to kill a Prince, though it be euen <hi>Saul,</hi> it is more then death,<note place="margin">Pſal. 105.15.25.</note> for hee is the Lordes <hi>anoynted,</hi> he is Gods miniſter. If <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo reuenged the iniurie that was done to his <hi>Ambaſſador,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sam. 1.14. Rom. 13.4. Dauids Iuſtice 2. Sam. 10.4. &amp; cap. 12.30.31.</note> vpon the king of <hi>Ammon,</hi> and all the <hi>Ammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> will God ſuffer, will God ſuffer his <hi>Vice-gerent,</hi> in his owne preſence, not to bee diſfigured, but deſtroyed of a priuate perſon,<note place="margin">And the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine. Vengeance.</note> eſpecially of a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect? Is God <hi>blind</hi> that he cannot ſée it? Is he <hi>improuident</hi> that he doth not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it? Is he <hi>vniuſt</hi> that he will not, or not <hi>omnipotent,</hi> that hee can of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge it?<note place="margin">The Traitors terrour.</note> O when any Traitor thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſuch a thought (conſidering with what a worlde of myracles God hath diſcouered them) his <hi>hand</hi> ſhould <hi>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,</hi> his <hi>head</hi> tremble, his <hi>bodie</hi> quake, his <hi>heart</hi> faile, and his <hi>ſoule</hi> faint: and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152155:33"/>
yet need not God worke any myracle, for euerie one that hath <hi>Dauids</hi> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, if there heart bee as like <hi>Dauids</hi> heart, as <hi>Dauids</hi> heart was to Gods heart, will preſently with <hi>Dauid</hi> (though it bee his <hi>Saule</hi> that is dead) both commaunde his execution,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.16. His reward to the Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lekite.</note> and giue this ſentence, <hi>Thy blood bee vpon thine owne head, for thine owne mouth hath teſtified againſt thee, ſaying, I haue ſlaine the Lords anointed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin">The third Cable.</note>The puniſhments of the diſloyall to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Since the <hi>haynouſneſſe</hi> of the Crime of treaſon is apparant, may it pleaſe you to make the puniſhments of treaſon apparant.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>That there is <hi>puniſhment,</hi> it appeareth by that of the Apoſtle, <hi>they that reſiſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 23.2.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhal receiue to themſelues Iudgement:</hi> of the gréeuouſneſſe of the Iudgement, we may be aſſured by the hainouſnes of the crime. And further, ſince, the Lawe requireth, that Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours pay <hi>life</hi> for <hi>life, eye</hi> for <hi>eye, tooth</hi> for <hi>tooth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eçclus. 21, 23, 24.25.</note> 
                     <hi>hand</hi> for <hi>hand, foote</hi> for <hi>foot,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152155:33"/>
burning</hi> for <hi>burning, wound</hi> for <hi>wound, ſtripe</hi> for <hi>ſtripe,</hi> what wounds, what burnings is he to endure that is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this Crime? howe many féete, howe many hands, howe many eyes, how many liues is he worthy to looſe, who ſo offendeth thoſe <hi>feete,</hi> of whom ſo many <hi>Thouſand</hi> féete, thoſe <hi>hands,</hi> of whome ſo many <hi>Thouſand</hi> handes, thoſe <hi>eyes,</hi> of whom ſo many <hi>Thouſand</hi> eyes, that <hi>life,</hi> whereon ſo many <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi> liues depend? Becauſe hee hath not ſo many féete, ſo many handes, ſo many eyes, ſo many liues, therefore is he puniſhed of <hi>God,</hi> and puniſhed of <hi>man.</hi> Puniſhed of man in his <hi>howſe,</hi> puniſhed in <hi>Lands,</hi> puniſhed in <hi>Offices,</hi> puniſhed in <hi>death,</hi> puniſhed in <hi>buriall,</hi> puniſhed in <hi>Name,</hi> and puniſhed in <hi>Poſteritie.</hi> Puniſhed in <hi>houſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In houſe.</note> for ſo was the houſe of <hi>Haman</hi> giuen to Quéene <hi>Eſter.</hi> Puniſhed in <hi>Landes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eſther. 8.1. In Landes. 2. Sam. 16.3.4.</note> ſo <hi>Siba</hi> hauing falſely accuſed <hi>Mephibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth</hi> to <hi>Dauid,</hi> vntill the troth was known, had all that was <hi>Mephiboſeths</hi> giuen him by <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In Offices.</note> Puniſhed in <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,</hi> ſo <hi>Abiathar</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> high Prieſt, though for his fidelitie to <hi>Dauid</hi> in all his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152155:34"/>
he had his life ſpared by <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Kings. 2.26.27.</note> yet <hi>Salomon</hi> caſt him cut from béeing <hi>Prieſt</hi> vnto the Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">In bodie pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, by drawing.</note>Puniſhed in <hi>body</hi> by impriſonment and tortures in life, after being drawn on a hurdle, from priſon to execution (to ſhewe how hee had béene drawne by brutiſh paſſions, and beaſtly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) by <hi>death,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">By death ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie.</note> and that not <hi>ordinarie,</hi> as an ordinarie <hi>Malefactor,</hi> but <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie,</hi> as an extraordinarie <hi>Malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor:</hi> a Théefe taking goods from any man is hanged, but becauſe the Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor offendeth no common member, but the head of the whole Eſtate, and in the head the whole eſtate, being draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, is firſt hanged, (for I will omit the more exquiſite puniſhments inflicted vpon Traitours in other Countreys) his <hi>ſecrets</hi> (to ſhewe hee was moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to bee begotten, or to beget o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) cut off and throwne into the fire before his face, his <hi>bellie</hi> ripped vp, his <hi>heart,</hi> the impure Veſſell of pernitious Trecherie, rent out &amp; thrown into the fire before his face, <hi>his bodie,</hi> hauing harboured ſo wicked a heart, hauing béene the Cage of a rebellious ſpirite, as it was in the bodie <hi>politique</hi> deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152155:34"/>
by Treaſon, from the head, and other members, ſo, now by the <hi>Axe,</hi> it is cut off from the head, and deuided into many quarters.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How be they puniſhed in buriall?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>In <hi>buriall,</hi> or rather by the defect of buriall, are they puniſhed. Was it not a puniſhment, that was foretolde by <hi>Ieremie,</hi> of <hi>Iehoiakim</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ioſiah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ieremie. 22.18.19.</note> he ſhall be buried as an <hi>Aſſe</hi> is buried, <hi>Euen drawne and caſt foorth without the walles of <hi>Ieruſalem?</hi>
                     </hi> But greater is the puniſhment of trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in their buriall, then was that of <hi>Iehoiakim, Iehoiakims</hi> buriall was the buriall of an <hi>Aſſe,</hi> the Traitors buriall is worſe then the buriall of an <hi>Aſſe:</hi> an Aſſe drawne without the gates of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and deuoured of dogs, or the beaſts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> field, is ſoone forgotten, but the Traitors bodie (though our merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Soueraigne dooth herein manie times ſhew great mercie) not drawne without the Gates,<note place="margin">Iudgement in buriall.</note> but fixed vpon the Gates of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> is not deuoured of the beaſts of the fields, and forgotten, but expoſed to the eyes, and reſerued in the memorie of men, that as his <hi>perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:152155:35"/>
attempts were an euill example to others, ſo his <hi>mangled</hi> and <hi>vnburied</hi> lims might be a heedfull and dreadfull <hi>caucat</hi> to others.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">In name.</note>
                     <hi>Wherein are they further puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>In <hi>name,</hi> a good <hi>name</hi> (ſaith the royall Preacher, <hi>is better then good oyntment, A good name,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is to be choſen aboue great riches, and louing fauour is aboue ſiluer and golde; but the name of the wicked</hi> (who ſo wicked as Rebels and Traitors) <hi>ſhall rot; rot?</hi> Well were it for them if there name could ſo rot that it might vtterly bee extinguiſhed, but being putrified, it giues a noyſome ſauor, ſo, that as that which <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid to <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leui, ye haue,</hi> So euery Traitors ofſpring may ſay of their Sire,<note place="margin">Gen. 34.30.</note> 
                     <hi>Thou haſt made me ſtinke among the inhabitants of the Land.</hi> What more odious ſmell to all true Engliſh hearts, Then the vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie memorie of <hi>Cade, Straw, Ket, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> and others of like deſerts, though greater eſtates?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Remaines there to the Rebell, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further puniſhment after death, but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152155:35"/>
in their <hi>buriall,</hi> and in their <hi>name?</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>To the Rebell there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth further puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for though in <hi>England</hi> they put not to death euery one of the familie as they did in <hi>Perſia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In poſteritie. Eſther. 16.18.</note> nor fiue of the Traitors neareſt kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke as they did in <hi>Macedonia,</hi> yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen among vs is the Traitour puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in his <hi>poſteritie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Since <hi>Kinges</hi> are Gods <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi>
                     </hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 13. Deut. 17.19. Obiec. againſt puniſhment in poſteritie.</note> 
                     <hi>and are to read in the word of God all the dayes of their life, I greatly mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile that they puniſh a Traytor in his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie, ſince God himſelfe hath ſayd, <hi>the ſame ſoule that ſinneth, it ſhall die.</hi>
                     </hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezeki. 18.20.</note> 
                     <hi>the ſonne ſhall not beare the iniquitie of the Father, neither ſhall the Father beare the iniquitie of the Sonne, but the righteouſnes of the righteous ſhalbe vppon him, and the wickedneſſe of the wicked ſhalbe vpon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>My Sonne, as <hi>Pithagoras</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned his Schollers to <hi>fiue yeares ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> that by hearing him and his more ancient Diſciples they might know what and how to ſpeake before they did ſpeake,<note place="margin">A caueat to youth.</note> ſo the Scripture char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth <hi>youth</hi> to be ſilent: the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152155:36"/>
vs to thinke others better then our ſelues, not <hi>raſhe</hi> like many igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants both in <hi>State,</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to reprooue that which they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not, but be thou moſt aduiſed in matters that be too high for thée, yet ſince I am perſwaded thou ſpeakeſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue <hi>inſtruction,</hi> then to vſe <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion,</hi> that thou mighteſt not, as in <hi>yeares,</hi> bee alſo in vnderſtanding a Child,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.20.</note> know that a man conſiſting of a <hi>bodie,</hi> which we haue from our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,<note place="margin">Gen. 5.3. Eccles. 12.7.</note> and a <hi>Soule</hi> which is giuen vs immediately from <hi>God,</hi> is Subiecte both to <hi>Corporall</hi> or <hi>Temporall,</hi> and to <hi>Spirituall,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ob. anſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> and <hi>eternall</hi> puniſhments, of which ſpirituall and eternall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, thou art to vnderſtand that of the Prophet, <hi>the ſame ſoule that ſinneth it ſhall die,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">God puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie.</note> 
                     <hi>the Sonne ſhall not beare the iniquitie of the Father:</hi> but for Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and Temporall puniſhments, the God of Heauen and earth viſiteth the iniquitie of the Father vpon the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren vnto the Third and Fourth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.5.</note> and iudgeth the houſe of <hi>Ely</hi> for euer,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 3.13.</note> becauſe his Sonnes ranne into a ſlaunder, and he ſtayd them not. Thus
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152155:36"/>
                     <hi>Cham</hi> in <hi>Chanaan, Ioab,</hi> and <hi>Gehezi,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 9.25. 2. Sam. 3.29. 2 Kings. 5.27. Math. 27.25.</note> in their poſteritie were puniſhed: thus the bloud of our <hi>Sauiour</hi> is vppon the Children of the <hi>Iewes</hi> vnto this day. Thus pray we in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Howe the Church of England prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that God would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the ſinnes of our Fore-fathers.</note> that the Lord would not remember the ſins of our Fore-fathers. And thus the <hi>Gods on earth</hi> haue puniſhed Traitors in their Children and Childrens chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Thus <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> becauſe <hi>Haman</hi> deſired to deſtroy <hi>Mordocheus</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruer of the King,<note place="margin">Eſter. 16.13, 14.</note> and innocent <hi>Eſter</hi> the Partaker of the Kingdome, whom when hee had taken away, his minde was for to haue layd wait for the king, &amp; by this meanes to tranſlate the <hi>king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of the <hi>Perſians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The ſeueritie of Perſia and Macedonia in this point.</note> vnto them of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia,</hi> was not onely (hauing béene the ſecond to the King) hanged on a <hi>Tree</hi> of Fiftie Cubittes highe, but alſo his Tenne Sonnes and all his Familie were hanged.<note place="margin">And the cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie of the Engliſh go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment.</note> Though in deteſtation of Treaſon, this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Traitour euen with the death of his poſteritie haue béene vſed, yet ſuch is the clemencie of our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh gouernment,</hi> that <hi>it</hi> ſparing their liues, puniſheth them onely in <hi>Lands,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152155:37"/>
howſes, goods, Offices, bloud,</hi> and <hi>honor.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Yee</note> Oh my <hi>Sonne,</hi> ſince as the fiſh ſwimmeth with the ſtreame, as the ſtreame floweth from the ſpring, as ſtones runne downe the hill, as the ſay aſcendeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the root to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> branches, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of parents deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">Fathers</note> what father though he could not be moued (yet where is there one ſo ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that is not mooued) with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>loſſe</hi> of his <hi>houſes,</hi> with the <hi>loſſe</hi> of lands, with the <hi>loſſe</hi> of his <hi>Offices,</hi> with the <hi>loſſe</hi> of his <hi>goodes,</hi> with the <hi>loſſe</hi> of his <hi>good name,</hi> with the <hi>loſſe</hi> of his <hi>libertie,</hi> with the <hi>loſſe</hi> of his <hi>life,</hi> by the <hi>imbowling</hi> &amp; <hi>diſmembring</hi> of his <hi>body,</hi> with the loſſe of <hi>Chriſtian burial,</hi> by his <hi>vnchriſtian be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour</hi> towards ſo <hi>Chriſtian</hi> a Prince, yet what father bred of Tigers brood,<note place="margin">be not</note> and fed with milke of Wolues, can bee ſo ſtonie hearted, as not euer to keepe himſelfe <hi>loyall</hi> to his Prince, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, leaſt hee vnnaturally &amp; moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly, bring thoſe iuſt puniſhments vpon his children, and childrens chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,<note place="margin">Traytours.</note> ſo inforcing them, if not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſe, yet (euen when they are ſilent) to proclaime to all future ages their
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152155:37"/>
                     <hi>aunceſtors</hi> diſloyal trecheries, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous diſloialties to their <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Countrey?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sir, I remember you diuided the puniſhments of Traitors into puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments inflicted vpon them by <hi>man,</hi> and puniſhments inflicted vpon them by <hi>God:</hi> remaineth there any more then theſe you haue alreadie named?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>There remaine more then theſe. Theſe are from <hi>God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iudgements from god and man vppon Traytors.</note> but by the <hi>miniſterie</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> and therefore I cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts inflicted by <hi>men:</hi> I call the other <hi>Gods</hi> puniſhments, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they come immediately from God. The puniſhments that are to be inflicted by the miniſterie of men, men by <hi>fauor,</hi> by <hi>policy,</hi> by <hi>power,</hi> ſometime eſcape: but thoſe that God himſelfe immediately inflicteth with his owne hand, no man can eſcape;<note place="margin">Prou. 21.30.</note> for ſaith <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> there is no <hi>Wiſdome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Si ſera, tamen certa. From god.</note> neither <hi>vnderſtanding,</hi> nor <hi>counſell</hi> againſt the Lord; and theſe be <hi>External, Internall,</hi> or <hi>Eternall.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>So many before, and ſo many more?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I pray you what be the externall;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Externall.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:152155:38"/>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>Then may we ſay that God immediately puniſheth Traitors <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally,</hi> where either <hi>ordinarie</hi> means be <hi>extraordinarily</hi> ſtirred vp,<note place="margin">Men.</note> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the land to puniſh thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt king Amon;</hi> or by meanes which man cannot vſe;<note place="margin">2. Kinges. 21.24.</note> ſo, for breuitie ſake to omit others, God himſelfe by <hi>Ieremie</hi> denounceth, the nation and kingdome which will not ſerue the ſame <hi>Nabuchodonozor</hi> king of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> and will not put their neckes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the yoke of the King of <hi>Babel, The ſame Nation will I viſite with the ſword,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ierem 27.8. Sword. Famine. Peſtilence. Leproſie. Fierie Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents. Earth Swallowing. Confederacy of vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les creatures. 2 Sam. 18.9.</note> 
                     <hi>and with the famine, and with the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, vntill I haue wholy giuen them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his handes,</hi> ſo puniſhed hee <hi>Miriam</hi> with <hi>leproſie</hi> as white as ſnow, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> with the fierie <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> with the <hi>earthes</hi> ſwallowing of them vp quicke, <hi>Abſolon</hi> with his own Mule to draw him, and his owne haire, and a great thicke Oke to hang him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How doth God puniſh them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>Not to ſpeake of other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall puniſhments,<note place="margin">Internall.</note> hee puniſheth
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152155:38"/>
them in conſcience: <hi>A good conſcience is,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, a continuall feaſt:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 15.15: Rom. 13.5.</note> but ſuch as wil not obey for <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience ſake,</hi> ſuch as will not ſubmit themſelues for the <hi>Lordes ſake,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.</note> are by the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of this good, and torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with an euill conſcience: and that this is a fearefull puniſhment, wee may learne of the <hi>Wiſeman: A fearefull thing is it,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>when malice is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Wiſd. 17.10.</note> by (which another ſaith, <hi>is more then a Thouſand witneſſes</hi>) her owne teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, and a conſcience that is tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, doth euer forecaſt cruell things. Theſe be thoſe <hi>furies</hi> whereof the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 2.15.</note> thoſe accuſing <hi>thoughts</hi> wherof the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that neuer dying-<hi>worme,</hi> whereof the <hi>Euangelicall Prophet,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eſay. 66.24. Mark. 9.44, 46, 48.</note> and he whom the <hi>Euangelicall</hi> Prophet did foretell, that booke whereof S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Reuel. 20.11, 12.</note> 
                     <hi>That it ſhall be opened when the earth and heauen flie away from his face that ſhall ſit on the great white throne. This,</hi> when they are abroade,<note place="margin">Leuit. 26.36.</note> though there be but the ſound of a leaf ſhaken, chaſeth them: <hi>this,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be within,<note place="margin">Prou. 28.1.</note> maketh them flie though none purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them: <hi>this writing</hi> in their heart,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152155:39"/>
like the hand-writing (which <hi>Baltha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> ſaw vpon the walles,<note place="margin">Dan. 5.5, 6.</note> when they are in the height of their pride, will cauſe their <hi>countenance</hi> to bee <hi>chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,</hi> their <hi>thoughts</hi> to bee <hi>troubled,</hi> the <hi>ioints</hi> of their <hi>loynes</hi> to bee <hi>looſed,</hi> and their <hi>knees</hi> to ſmite one againſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 24.6.</note> 
                     <hi>This</hi> if they cut but the lap of the Princes garment, will <hi>touch</hi> them at the <hi>heart. This,</hi> if they offer violence to their <hi>Lord,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts. 2.37.</note> will <hi>pricke</hi> them at the heart.<note place="margin">Gen. 4.13.</note> 
                     <hi>This,</hi> as it did <hi>Cain</hi> for his <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers blood,</hi> will much more for their <hi>Lieges blood,</hi> make their owne hearts to thinke, and their owne mouthes to ſay, <hi>that their puniſhment is greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they can beare, that their ſinne is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then can be forgiuen them. This,</hi> as it did <hi>Iudas,</hi> will make their <hi>ſoules</hi> to loath and abhorre their <hi>bribes</hi> receiued for their <hi>trecherie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 27.3, 4.5.</note> and their <hi>handes</hi> to caſt them downe, and their <hi>tongues</hi> to proclaime <hi>that they haue betraied inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood. This,</hi> will make their owne handes to hang them,<note place="margin">Math. 27.5. Luk. 10.17. 2 Sam. 17.23.</note> though like <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> they haue faith to worke <hi>Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> or like <hi>Achitophel</hi> they can giue <hi>counſail,</hi> eas if one aſked at the <hi>oracle</hi>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:152155:39"/>
of God. Were there no other I would ſay with <hi>Iuuenall.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.23.</note>
                  </p>
                  <q xml:lang="lat">
                     <l>—Cur tamen hos tu</l>
                     <l>Euaſiſſe putes, quos diri conſcia facti,<note place="margin">Iuuenal.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Mens habet attonitos, &amp; ſur do verbere</l>
                     <l>-caedit</l>
                     <l>Occultum quatienti animo tortore</l>
                     <l>-flagellum?</l>
                  </q>
                  <q xml:lang="eng">
                     <l>
                        <hi>-How deem'ſt thou them</hi> ac-quite,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whom</hi> guiltie <hi>minde of</hi> fact <hi>ſo foule doth</hi> frighte:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And</hi> ſcourge vn-ſeene <hi>doth beate with</hi> vn-heard bloe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Their</hi> hang-man <hi>reſtleſſe</hi> Conſcience, biting <hi>ſoe?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O hatefull treaſon: <hi>how art thou enuironed with fearefull iudgements?</hi> iudgement <hi>in houſe and lands,</hi> iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>in Offices,</hi> iudgement <hi>in</hi> body, iudgement <hi>in</hi> buriall, iudgement <hi>in</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <hi>and reputation,</hi> iudgement <hi>in</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Thus pray we all.</note> 
                     <hi>iudgements <hi>powred vppon thy head, euen by the hand of God</hi> eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, <hi>and this of</hi> conſcience, internally! O <hi>moſt mightie and moſt mercifull
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152155:40"/>
God, of thy infinite mercie, by thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite grace, bleſſe mee euermore from this ſinne, that I may be euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more bleſſed from the puniſhments of this ſinne.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>As <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> wiſhed, that men would dayly thinke of <hi>hell,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chriſoſtomes wiſh.</note> and ſpeake of <hi>hell,</hi> that ſo by feare thereof, they might bee drawne from ſinne, ſo I wiſh they would dayly thinke of,<note place="margin">The Authors wiſh.</note> and dayly ſpeake of the iudgements which <hi>reſiſters</hi> and <hi>Rebelles</hi> do receiue, that ſo they might be driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi> but the better to driue them from it, know there is another iudgement vpon <hi>traitours</hi> more <hi>greeuous</hi> then any of theſe, more <hi>greeuous</hi> then all of theſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Is it poſsible?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>If <hi>Lucifer</hi> for <hi>Rebellion</hi> fell from <hi>heauen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eternall.</note> if <hi>Adam</hi> for diſobedience was caſt out of <hi>paradiſe,</hi> his whole po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie infected with <hi>originall</hi> ſinne, made ſubiect to <hi>death,</hi> became the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>wrath,</hi> then no maruell though <hi>ſedition</hi> bee ſuch a <hi>fruite</hi> of the fleſh, as whoſoeuer is guiltie of it, it hindreth him from the inheriting the <hi>kingdome</hi>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:152155:40"/>
of God. If it ſeemed greeuous to <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> lying in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gal 5.20, 21. 2 Sam. 14.32.</note> not once in two yeeres to ſee the face of <hi>Dauid,</hi> O how greeuous ſhall it be for all <hi>Rebels,</hi> (dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without repentance) neyther to come into the new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Paine of loſſe.</note> nor to ſee the <hi>face</hi> of God for euer? if it be a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous thing to lie fettered in a <hi>priſon,</hi> O how greeuous is it with the vngodly, (of whom <hi>Rebels</hi> be in the firſt ranke) to be turned into <hi>hell,</hi> and there to lie bound <hi>hand</hi> and <hi>foote?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Paine of ſence Acerbitie. Math. 25.41.</note> wouldeſt thou knowe the ſharpneſſe of thoſe paines? <hi>Chriſt</hi> telleth thée, <hi>they goe into fire:</hi> wouldeſt thou know the <hi>time</hi> they do laſt? he calleth it <hi>euerlaſting:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eternitie.</note> wouldeſt thou knowe the <hi>companie</hi> they ſhall haue?<note place="margin">Societie.</note> he telleth thee the <hi>diuell</hi> &amp; his <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels:</hi> wouldeſt thou haue it further expreſſed? aſſure thy ſelfe that as the <hi>ioyes</hi> of the <hi>godly,</hi> purchaſed by the <hi>obedience</hi> of the <hi>ſonne</hi> of <hi>God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Vnſpeakable.</note> are ſuch, as <hi>the eye of man hath not ſeene, nor the eare of man hath not heard, nor can enter into mans heart,</hi> ſo alſo be the <hi>paines</hi> and <hi>torments</hi> prepared for the the <hi>diſobedient</hi> ſonnes of men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The father of mercyes of his
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152155:41"/>
great mercie, keepe mee and all my countrey-men from this <hi>crime,</hi>
                     </hi>
                     <note place="margin">His wiſh to the Engliſh.</note> 
                     <hi>and from theſe <hi>paines.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin">The fourth Cable.</note>The reward of the loyall to Caeſar.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>He is the miniſter of God for thy wealth:<note place="margin">Rom. 13.3.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Doe well, ſo ſhalt thou haue prayſe of the ſame.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of the Loyall.</note> The <hi>rewards</hi> of <hi>loyaltie</hi> bee either <hi>generall</hi> to all, or <hi>particular</hi> to ſome. generall to all, this <hi>Daniell</hi> declareth ſomewhat darkely in the tree,<note place="margin">Dan. 4.7.8.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Beholde I ſaw a tree in the middeſt of the earth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Darkely ſha-</note> 
                     <hi>&amp; the heigth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was great, a great tree and ſtrong, and the heigth thereof reached to heauen, and the ſight thereof vnto the ends of all the earth. The boughs thereof were faire, and the fruit thereof much, and in it was meate for all, it made a ſhadow vnder it, for the beaſts of the field, and the fowles of heauen dwelt in the boughes thereof, and all fleſh fed of it. Eſay</hi> more plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">dowed. Eſay. 32. Plainely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth.</note> 
                     <hi>That man ſhall be as a hiding place from the winde, and as a refuge for the tempeſt, and as riuers of waters in a drie place, and as the ſhadow of a great rocke
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152155:41"/>
in a wearie land.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">If Iſraell for her peace muſt ſeeke Ierem. 29.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the peace of Babel, Wil not Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land for her good ſeeke the good of Elizabeth?</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore, as <hi>Ieremy</hi> willed the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> to ſeeke the proſperitie of the cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie whether they were carried, ſo I beſeech all true <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> to ſeeke the proſperitie of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> vnder whom they are gouerned: &amp; <hi>Ieremias</hi> reaſon may induce them, for in the <hi>peace</hi> thereof, they ſhall haue <hi>peace,</hi> in the <hi>proſperitie</hi> thereof, they ſhall haue <hi>proſperitie,</hi> in the <hi>glory</hi> thereof they ſhal haue <hi>glory. Iudah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> dwelt without feare, euery man vnder his <hi>vine,</hi> and vnder his <hi>fig-tree,</hi> from <hi>Dan,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">That Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon was to Iſraell, that Elizabeth is to England. Perticuler re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards for the loyall. Prou. 22.24. Prou. 16.15.</note> euen to <hi>Berſheba,</hi> all the dayes of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon:</hi> haue not <hi>England</hi> doone the like, from <hi>Barwick to ſaint Michaels Mount,</hi> all the dayes of <hi>Elizabeth?</hi> But if any man <hi>through diligence, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth before Kings, not before the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſort</hi> of men, hee ſhal find that <hi>in the light of the Kings countenance is life, and his fauour is as a cloud of the latter raine.</hi> If I regard <hi>a houſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Houſe. Eſter. 2.21, 8.2. Externall pompe. Gen. 41.43.</note> I ſee it brought <hi>Mordecay</hi> from ſitting at the Kings <hi>gate,</hi> to be placed ouer the <hi>houſe</hi> of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous <hi>Haman:</hi> If I reſpect outward <hi>ſhew?</hi> I ſee <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in the ſecond Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152155:42"/>
of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Mardocheus</hi> vpon the Kings horſe in <hi>royall</hi> apparrell, a crowne of <hi>gold</hi> on his head,<note place="margin">Eſter. 6.8.11</note> 
                     <hi>Haman</hi> proclaiming before him in the ſtreetes of <hi>Shuſan, thus ſhall it be done to the man whom the King will honour,</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> in <hi>Babilon</hi> clothed in <hi>purple,</hi> and a chaine of <hi>golde</hi> about his necke. If <hi>eſtimation</hi> of the people, for it, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> was honoured with his <hi>Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand:</hi> if <hi>fauour</hi> and <hi>frendſhip</hi> of the <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyeſt, this</hi> knit the ſoule of <hi>Ionathan</hi> eldeſt Sonne to the King, to the ſoule of <hi>Dauid:</hi> If alliance with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, <hi>this</hi> eſpouſed <hi>Ioſeph</hi> the priſoner to <hi>Aſenath</hi> daughter of <hi>Potipherah</hi> prieſt, or Prince of <hi>On, this</hi> brought <hi>Dauid</hi> the Shepheard to <hi>Michall</hi> Daughter of <hi>Saule</hi> King of <hi>Iſraell:</hi> If <hi>power</hi> and <hi>authoritie, this</hi> made <hi>Ioſeph 2.</hi> in <hi>Egypt, Mordecai 2.</hi> in <hi>Perſia,</hi> &amp; <hi>Daniel 2.</hi> in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon:</hi> If <hi>good</hi> to our <hi>nation, this</hi> lift vp <hi>Mordecay</hi> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his people from deſtruction: If the <hi>good</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of God, <hi>this,</hi> with the bleſſing of God vpon him, who aymed at ſo good an end, made <hi>Zorobabel</hi> gratious in the eyes of <hi>Darius:</hi> if <hi>a good name,</hi>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:152155:42"/>
and <hi>eternall renowne</hi> (what more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious then a good name, eſpecially <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized?) This</hi> cauſed <hi>Mordecaies</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and <hi>Mordecaies</hi> magnificence to be celebrated in the Chronicles of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> and <hi>Perſia,</hi> this,<note place="margin">Eſter. 10.2.3.</note> 
                     <hi>eternized</hi> them in the <hi>neuer-fayling</hi> word of the <hi>eternall</hi> God: If the <hi>good</hi> of our <hi>poſteritie,</hi> (a dead man ſtil ſeemeth to liue in his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie) <hi>Barzillaie</hi> when <hi>Dauid</hi> fled from <hi>Abſolon</hi> prouided him of ſuſtenance ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Mahaynaim,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Barzillai du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfull, loyall.</note> and after <hi>Dauids</hi> victory, conducted him ouer <hi>Iordane, Dauid</hi> for this not onely offered to feed <hi>Barzillai</hi> with him in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and to doe for him whatſoeuer he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of him,<note place="margin">Dauid.</note> &amp; when he would needs depart, bleſſed him, &amp; kiſſed him, but alſo for his ſake accepted of <hi>Chimham,</hi> and dealt royally with him in his life, but alſo in his death-bed, commanded <hi>Salomon</hi> to ſhew kindnes to the ſonnes of <hi>Barzillai</hi> the <hi>Giliadite,</hi> and to let them be among them that eate at his table<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>O bleſſed loialtie</hi> bleſſing the <hi>loi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> not onely <hi>generally,</hi> with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and <hi>publique,</hi> but alſo <hi>particularly,</hi> with the <hi>priuate good,</hi> good in <hi>poſſeſſion,</hi>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:152155:43"/>
good in <hi>eſtimation,</hi> good in <hi>authoritie,</hi> in <hi>honor,</hi> in <hi>fauour,</hi> in <hi>alliance,</hi> in <hi>name,</hi> in <hi>religion,</hi> in <hi>fame,</hi> in <hi>poſteritie.</hi> O bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed loyalty! Is it not enough that thou bleſſeſt vs with ſo many fauours, but others for vs, not vs and others at this preſent; but others for vs herere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after?<note place="margin">Gratefully.</note> 
                     <hi>Barzillai</hi> was loyall to <hi>Dauid</hi> in his diſtreſſe, <hi>Dauid</hi> was gratefull to <hi>Barzillai,</hi> when he was deliuered from diſtreſſe, gratefull in <hi>life,</hi> grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in <hi>death,</hi> death makes men forget their owne children, their own ſelues, death and the panges of death, could not make <hi>Dauid</hi> to forget <hi>Barzillaies</hi> loyalty; death had power to ende and cut off <hi>Dauids life,</hi> death had not power to end or cut off <hi>Dauids gratuity</hi> for <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zillaies</hi> loyalty,<note place="margin">Royall.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> both might remaine after death, euen at death, he charged his ſonne to ſhew kindnes to <hi>Barzil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laies</hi> ſonne,<note place="margin">Both</note> to <hi>Barzillaies</hi> ſonne? to <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zillaies</hi> ſonns: and ſuch kindnes, that they ſhould eate with him at his table:<note place="margin">Immortall.</note> 
                     <hi>Barzillai</hi> dead, <hi>Barzillaies loyalty, Dauid</hi> dead, <hi>Dauids gratuitie</hi> brightly ſhineth in their poſteritie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good father, you ſhewing Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152155:43"/>
to be ſet ouer me of <hi>God,</hi> my duety to <hi>God</hi> moued me to performe my duety to <hi>Caeſar:</hi> you ſhewing me of the haynouſnes of the <hi>crime</hi> of diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, my heart abhorred it, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech God no diſloyalty come into my heart, much leſſe breake out of my <hi>tongue</hi> in ſpeaking, or my <hi>hand</hi> in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: you ſhewing the iudgementes incident to the <hi>diſloyall,</hi> if I had ſo little grace, and ſo little reaſon that nought elſe could, feare of them may keepe me from this <hi>crime:</hi> but now you ſhew the great benefits that ariſe out of <hi>loyalty,</hi> you haue inflamed my heart with a more feruent loue of the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>Let me then my <hi>ſonne</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inflame it. If <hi>Caeſar</hi> being ouer ſuch a people as <hi>Salomon</hi> was, and as <hi>Paul</hi> was for all the Churches,<note place="margin">1 Kin. 3.8. 2 Cor. 11.28.</note> cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with the <hi>care</hi> of them daily, or bee thy <hi>merits</hi> be not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>moment,</hi> or there is not that opportunitie, to haue them knowen vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> &amp; therfore <hi>Caeſar</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſay with <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> (though <hi>Caeſar</hi> be as <hi>bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful</hi> &amp; <hi>royally</hi> grateful as <hi>Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi>) what <hi>honour,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eſter. 6.3.</note> &amp; <hi>dignitie</hi> hath beene
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152155:44"/>
giuen to <hi>Mordecai</hi> for this? Yet for the <hi>Publique</hi> good, (for which <hi>Curtius</hi> in <hi>Rome, Sampſon</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> many in many nations ſacrificed their liues) and in the publique, thy priuate good (though <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhould neuer heare if thou wert <hi>diſloyall,</hi> and therefore could not puniſh thee) <hi>yet</hi> giue <hi>Caeſars</hi> to <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke. 17.10. Math. 3.15. Rom. 13.5. 1. Pet. 2.13.</note> as the Lord Ieſus ſaith <hi>for dueties ſake,</hi> and <hi>for righteouſnes ſake,</hi> as ſaint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>for conſcience ſake,</hi> as ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>for the Lords ſake,</hi> and the Lord whoſe <hi>reward</hi> is with him, who will come <hi>quickly,</hi> whoſe <hi>word</hi> ſhal not paſſe away, (though <hi>heauen</hi> and <hi>earth</hi> paſſe away, will reward thee, though man doe not, whoſe <hi>life</hi> is a <hi>vapoure;</hi> whoſe <hi>fleſh</hi> is <hi>graſſe,</hi> whoſe <hi>rewards</hi> be <hi>temporarie</hi>) the Lord, I ſay, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thee, reward them, as elſe hee will puniſh thee <hi>Externally, Internally, Eternally.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Gods rewards of loyaltie.</note>Externally, (for our <hi>good Subiect</hi> is to bee a good <hi>man,</hi> our true <hi>Caeſarian</hi> to be a true <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> otherwiſe, if he goe not out with <hi>Abſolon,</hi> I ſuſpect his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out with <hi>Adoniah,</hi> &amp; neither good man, nor good Subiect is he, who gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152155:44"/>
not to <hi>God</hi> thoſe thinges which be <hi>Gods,</hi> and for Gods ordinance to <hi>Caeſar</hi> thoſe thinges which are <hi>Caeſars) Bleſſed</hi> ſhalt thou be in the <hi>Cittie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Externall</hi> Deut. 28.3, 4, 5, 6.</note> and <hi>bleſſed</hi> alſo in the <hi>field, bleſſed</hi> ſhall be the <hi>fruite</hi> of thy <hi>bodie,</hi> and the <hi>fruite</hi> of thy <hi>ground,</hi> and the <hi>fruite</hi> of thy <hi>Cattell,</hi> the <hi>encreaſe</hi> of thy <hi>Kine,</hi> and the <hi>flocks</hi> of thy <hi>Sheepe, bleſſed</hi> ſhall thy <hi>baſkette</hi> be and thy <hi>dowe, bleſſed</hi> ſhalt thou bée when thou commeſt <hi>in,</hi> and <hi>bleſſed</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo when thou goeſt <hi>out.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How internally?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>What greater <hi>bleſſing</hi> then the ſoules <hi>banquet,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Internall</hi> Prou. 15.15.</note> then the ſoules con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall <hi>banquet?</hi> a good <hi>conſcience</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> is a continuall <hi>Feaſt,</hi> what <hi>mellodie</hi> to that ſwéete harmonie of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing <hi>thoughtes,</hi> what <hi>comfort</hi> to that moſt comfortable aſſurance that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening of the <hi>Booke</hi> will ſhewe,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.15. Rom. 8 16. Reuel. 20.12. Luke 10.20.</note> that our names are written in <hi>Heauen?</hi> when others <hi>wringe</hi> their handes for <hi>greefe,</hi> this will make thée <hi>clappe</hi> thy handes for <hi>ioye,</hi> when others <hi>tremble</hi> thou ſhalt <hi>triumph:</hi> This maketh thée to ſléepe <hi>quietly,</hi> to wake <hi>cheerefully,</hi> to bee alone <hi>without feare:</hi> and with
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152155:45"/>
others without <hi>diſtruſt,</hi> in thy affaires <hi>confident,</hi> in thy recreation <hi>comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:</hi> If Rebels be behinde thée, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thée,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 10.9, 12.</note> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Ammonits</hi> &amp; the <hi>Aramites</hi> were before <hi>Ioab,</hi> and behinde him, yet thou wouldeſt reſolue with <hi>Ioab, bee ſtrong, and let vs bee valiant for our people, and for the Citties of our God, and let the Lord doe that which is good in his eyes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And how eternally?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>Eternally, when after all thy loyaltie to thy <hi>Soueraigne</hi> Prince,<note place="margin">Eternall.</note> the <hi>Soueraigne</hi> of all Princes ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance thee into the holy <hi>Citie</hi> newe <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem:</hi> was it not ſayd of thée by the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reuel. 21.10.</note> 
                     <hi>verie excellent things are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of thee thou Cittie of God?</hi> hath not the diuine <hi>Aegle,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 87.3. Reuel. 21.10. Matter. 18. Streete. 21. Splendor. 11.</note> the <hi>Aegle</hi> of diuines, ſaide of thée, <hi>that thou art pure gould like vnto cleare glaſſe?</hi> of thy ſtréete, <hi>that it is pure gould</hi> as <hi>ſhining glaſſe?</hi> of thy ſhining, <hi>that it is like vnto a ſtone moſt pretious,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Foundations of the Wall. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>as a Iaſper ſtone cleare as Chriſtall?</hi> of the foundations of thy wall, <hi>that they are garniſhed with all manner of pretious ſtones?</hi> of thy twelue gates,<note place="margin">Gates. 12, and 21.</note> 
                     <hi>that they are twelue pearles?</hi> of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152155:45"/>
euery gate, <hi>that it is of one pearle?</hi> of the keepers of the twelue gates,<note place="margin">Porters. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>that they are twelue Angels?</hi> of thy light, <hi>that it is the glory of God &amp; the lambe?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Light. 23.</note> of thy Temple, <hi>that the Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, &amp; the Lambe are thy Temple?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Temple. 22.</note> of the puritie of the Inhabitants,<note place="margin">Puritie of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants. 21.27.</note> 
                     <hi>that there ſhall enter into thee, no vncleane thinge, neither whatſoeuer worketh ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination, or lyes?</hi> of thy recordes,<note place="margin">Recordes. 20.12.</note> 
                     <hi>that they bee the Booke of life?</hi> of thy water, <hi>that it is not that <hi>aqua vitae,</hi>
                     </hi>
                     <note place="margin">Water. 22.1.</note> 
                     <hi>or <hi>aqua Caeleſtis,</hi> that is vſed on earth for bodies, but for ſoules it is a pure Riuer of water of life, cleare as Chriſtall, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding out of the throne of God, and of the Lambe: the ſoules of them that drinke of this ſhall liue for euer:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tree. 2.</note> Of thy trée being in the middeſt of thy ſtreete, and of eyther ſide of thy Riuer, <hi>that it is the tree of life? that it beareth 12 maner of fruits?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Fruite. ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem. Immunities. 3, 5. Eſtate. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>that it giueth fruit euery moneth? that the leaues thereof ſerue to heale the Nations with?</hi> of thy immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>that there ſhalbe no more curſe, no night, no need of candle, nor light of the Sun?</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſtate of thy inhabitants, <hi>that they ſhall liue and raigne for euermore?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:152155:46"/>Remember my <hi>ſon,</hi> who is the <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Caeſar,</hi> whoſe <hi>ordinance</hi> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt that reſiſt <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the <hi>iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</hi> they receyue that reſiſt <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the <hi>rewards</hi> of them that <hi>obey Caeſar,</hi> God in <hi>Caeſar.</hi> For as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo I ſay to thée,<note place="margin">The Author</note> and in thée to <hi>England, I call hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth to recorde this day againſt you,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">His conteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to <hi>England.</hi> Deut. 30, 19.</note> 
                     <hi>that I haue ſet before you death and life, bleſsing and curſing, therefore chuſe life, that thou and thy ſeede may liue,</hi> and with Ieremie, <hi>But if you will not heare this, my ſoule ſhall weepe in ſecrete for your pride, and mine eye ſhall weepe and drop downe teares.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deare Father, neither ſhall hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen nor earth, by the grace of the <hi>Almightie,</hi>
                     </hi>
                     <note place="margin">His proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Ierem. 13.17. Acts. 2.2.</note> 
                     <hi>beare record agaynſt me, neither ſhall your <hi>ſoule</hi> weepe in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, nor your <hi>eyes</hi> drop downe <hi>teares,</hi> for my <hi>Diſobedience,</hi> either in <hi>Thought Worde,</hi> or <hi>Deede:</hi> for more doe not the foure winds purifie the aire, then theſe foure propoſitions haue purified my heart, and I hope that that holy ſpirit, which came downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with a mightie and ruſhing wind, will enable me to holde my courſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152155:46"/>
the <hi>wind,</hi> and <hi>tide</hi> of all <hi>traitors,</hi> and therfore as you diuided the breach of allegiance, into <hi>Thought, Word,</hi> and <hi>Deede,</hi> ſo I pray you ſhew me ſome branches of allegiance, that I may the more certainly ſee what I owe to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>My ſonne, for thy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſake, vnderſtand,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sixe braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance.</hi> 2 Chro. 9.18.</note> that as there were ſixe ſteppes to the <hi>throne</hi> of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon:</hi> ſo there be ſixe partes of thy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Howe I pray you, ſhall I knowe them?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>Séeſt thou the <hi>ſworde</hi> in her hande, or caried before her:<note place="margin">Rom. 13.4. Pſal. 21.3. Pſal. 45.6. 2. Chron. 9.17 Rom 13.4. 1 King. 2.15.</note> the <hi>Crowne</hi> of pure golde vpon her <hi>head:</hi> the <hi>Scepter</hi> of righteouſneſſe which ſhe doth ſway: the magnificent <hi>throne</hi> whereon ſhe doth ſit: her <hi>perſon</hi> which is the miniſter of God for thy wealth, and the Lord by whom the kingdome came vnto her?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bleſſed be God I doe ſee them, and God long ſo bleſſe me, that long I may ſee them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>The <hi>ſworde</hi> exacteth <hi>feare:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Feare. Honour.</note> the <hi>Crowne</hi> importeth <hi>honour:</hi> the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152155:47"/>
                     <hi>Scepter</hi> requireth <hi>obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Obedience. Tribute. Defence. Prayer.</note> the <hi>throne</hi> deſerueth <hi>tribute,</hi> the perſon meriteth <hi>defence,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Lord</hi> commandeth <hi>praier.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt, I beſeech you inſtruct me in the firſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Feare.</note>
                     <hi>Feare</hi> is to be giuen to <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> ſo teacheth <hi>humanitie,</hi> ſo teacheth <hi>diuinitie.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Feare of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces taught both in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie and Diuinitie.</note> For humanitie, <hi>Periander</hi> hee ſaith, <hi>Feare Princes.</hi> For Diuinitie, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Feare the Lord and the King.</hi> If I be a maſter, doth God ſay where is my feare? If I be a <hi>maiſter,</hi> may the King ſay,<note place="margin">Prou. 24.21.</note> 
                     <hi>Where is my feare?</hi> Be ye afrayed of the <hi>ſword,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>ſword</hi> will be auenged of <hi>wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Malach. 1.6. Feare due to Caeſar, as to a Father, Iob. 19.29. as to an auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. God diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate perſons,</note> Would any priuate man ſtrike mens hearts with <hi>feare?</hi> Let him know that God hath not giuen the <hi>ſword</hi> of Princes to <hi>priuate</hi> men. Concerning <hi>theſe,</hi> he ſaid in the law <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> hee decréed before the law, <hi>Who ſo ſheddeth mans bloud, by man ſhall his bloud be ſhed,</hi> affirmed in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, <hi>All that take the ſword, ſhall periſh with the ſword,</hi> confirmed in the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.13. Gen. 9.6. Math. 26.52. Reuel. 13.10.</note> 
                     <hi>If any man kill with a ſword, hee muſt be killed by a ſword:</hi> but of euerie one of <hi>thoſe</hi> he ſaith by the Apoſtle, <hi>He
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152155:47"/>
is the miniſter of god to take vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce on him that doth euil.</hi> Is he only for a <hi>ſhew?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 31, 4. and the Prince. Prou. 16.14. Prou. 19.12.</note> No, ſaith <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the wrath of the King is as the meſſengers of death:</hi> And again, <hi>the kings wrath is like the roring of a Lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The ſword not for a bare ſhew.</note> No, ſaith <hi>Paul, <hi>he beareth not the ſword for nought. Hence</hi>
                     </hi> may it be that <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> affirmeth of the <hi>ſeditions</hi> that <hi>their deſtruction ſhal riſe ſodainely.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sodaine in the deſtruction of the ſeditious. Prou. 24.22. To what we muſt take heede.</note> I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with <hi>Salomon</hi> aduertiſe thee, to take heede to the <hi>mouth</hi> of the <hi>King.</hi> If thou wilt haue another reaſon added to the former, he ſaith, <hi>where the worde of the king is, there is power:</hi> If thou wilt know how great power,<note place="margin">Ecces. 8.2, 4.</note> the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> of thoſe <hi>Squires</hi> of the <hi>bodie</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Orations before <hi>Darius</hi> and his <hi>Nobles</hi> telleth thee,<note place="margin">The greatnes of the Kinges power..</note> 
                     <hi>though men rule by land, and ſea, and ouer all things in them, yet is the king greater,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Eſdr. 4.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</note> for <hi>he ruleth all things, and is Lord of them.</hi> If hee bid them make <hi>Warre</hi> one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they doe it: If he ſend them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>enemies,</hi> they goe, and breake downe mountaines, and wals, and Towers, they kill and are killed, and doe not paſſe the <hi>commaundement</hi> of the <hi>king:</hi> If he bid <hi>kill,</hi> they kill:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152155:48"/>
if he ſay <hi>ſpare,</hi> they ſpare: if he bid <hi>ſmite,</hi> they ſmite: if he bid them make <hi>deſolate,</hi> they make deſolate: If he bid <hi>build,</hi> they build: If he bid <hi>cut</hi> of, they cut of. Feare the <hi>ſword</hi> of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the <hi>drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> ſword of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>powerful</hi> draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en ſword of <hi>Caeſar.</hi> But eſpecially (for a wiſe man ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> feareth and departeth from euil,<note place="margin">
                        <p>Prou. 14.16. A difference of the wiſe man and the foole.</p>
                        <p>Caeſar puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the tranſgreſsor of the lawes of the land. Caeſar puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor of the lawes of God. Rom. 13.</p>
                        <p>Wherevpon and to what end this feare beareth the eyes of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects.</p>
                        <p>What the ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuous ſubiect feareth. Iob. 29.8.</p>
                     </note> but a foole rageth, and is careleſſe) feare to commit <hi>euill, feare</hi> the breach of the <hi>lawes</hi> of the land, <hi>feare</hi> the breach of the <hi>lawe</hi> of God. <hi>feare</hi> the breach of the lawes of the land, for the <hi>king</hi> of the land will take <hi>vengeance</hi> of the tranſgreſſions of the lawes of the land. <hi>Feare</hi> the breach of the <hi>lawes</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> for the <hi>King</hi> of the land, being the <hi>Miniſter</hi> of God, wil take <hi>vengeance</hi> on them that tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe the lawe of God. This feare carieth one eie of the Subiect vpon the Princes <hi>ſword,</hi> that he neuer prouoke it: the other eye vpon the <hi>offence,</hi> that he neuer commit it: he feareth <hi>blame,</hi> as much as <hi>paine: reproach,</hi> as much as <hi>torment: diſhonor</hi> as much as <hi>death.</hi> So the young men fearing to be ſeene, (where and when they ſhould not)
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152155:48"/>
when they ſawe <hi>Iob,</hi> hid themſelues. This <hi>feare,</hi> as the Porters keepe <hi>Traytours</hi> out of the <hi>Princes</hi> Courte,<note place="margin">
                        <p>This feare is a porter of the heart.</p>
                        <p>The ballaſt of the ſoule.</p>
                        <p>The bridle of the affections The naile that faſteneth vs in our duties.</p>
                        <p>Reuel. 12.14. The two eyes of this feare be two wings wherewith we flie from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. Heſt. 15.5.6.7.11.</p>
                        <p>The two wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting women wherewith a ſubiects mind endued is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the ſeruice and fauour of his Soueraigne. Rom, 13.7.</p>
                     </note> keepeth <hi>treacherie</hi> out of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes heartes. This <hi>feare,</hi> as <hi>bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt</hi> preſerueth the <hi>ſhippe</hi> from being ouerblowen of the <hi>winde,</hi> keepeth the <hi>ſoule</hi> of the Subiect that ſhee be not ouerthrowen by others <hi>flatterie,</hi> or her owne preſumption. This <hi>feare,</hi> as a <hi>bridle,</hi> curbes vs from all <hi>diſobedience.</hi> This feare, as a naile fixeth vs firme in our dueties. This <hi>feare,</hi> as the woman in the <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> with the two <hi>winges,</hi> fledde from the <hi>Dragon,</hi> with her two <hi>eies</hi> flyeth from all <hi>Rebellion</hi> the ſeede of the Dragon. This <hi>feare</hi> as <hi>Eſther</hi> with her two <hi>maides</hi> comming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the preſence of <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> was gratiouſly entertayned, with theſe two <hi>eyes</hi> comes into the ſeruice and fauour of her Soueraigne. This <hi>feare</hi> giue to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to <hi>Ceſar</hi> thou oweſt this <hi>feare.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The God of heauen imprint this <hi>feare,</hi> in my <hi>heart.</hi> But to this feare am I to adioyne <hi>honour?</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:152155:49"/>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Honour.</note>If as among the <hi>Elements</hi> the <hi>fire</hi> is moſt excellent: If as among the <hi>creatures</hi> on earth, <hi>man</hi> is moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.41.</note> If as among the <hi>ſtarres</hi> of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, one <hi>ſtarre</hi> differeth from another ſtarre in <hi>glorie:</hi> So <hi>Caeſar</hi> (amongeſt men) by the finger of God is made moſt <hi>excellent:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Honor are we to giue to Caeſar, leaſt we beare falſe witneſſe.</note> Who will not (ſince <hi>honour</hi> is as the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſayth, a teſtimonie of <hi>excellencie</hi>) giue <hi>honour</hi> to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> leaſt they beare falſe witnes not againſt their <hi>neighbor,</hi> not againſt <hi>Caeſar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Leaſt wee breake the Canon of the Apoſtle. Rom. 13.7.</note> but againſt <hi>God</hi> who hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted <hi>Caeſar:</hi> leaſt they breake the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtle, Giue honour to whom ye owe honour:</hi> leaſt they be <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt,,</hi> not giuing to euerie man his <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Leaſt wee bee vniuſt. Leaſt wee tranſgreſſe Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. Exod. 20.12. Lamen. 4.16. Leaſt we giue iuſte occaſion of complaint againſt our Nation.</note> leaſt they tranſgreſſe <hi>Gods</hi> owne <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement:</hi> leaſt, as <hi>Ieremie</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of the <hi>Iewes, They reuerenced not the face of the Prieſtes,</hi> ſome other complaine of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> they reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced <hi>not the face of the Prince?</hi> The <hi>Prieſt</hi> is a <hi>figure</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> is the <hi>figure</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> If <hi>Nabuchodonozor</hi> ſetting vp a deade <hi>Image,</hi> preuailed with his <hi>vngodly</hi> ſubiects at the ſound of <hi>muſicall</hi> Inſtruments,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.1.7.</note> to worſhip it
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152155:49"/>
with <hi>honour</hi> forbidden of <hi>God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <p>Shall not God rather preuaile with his Seruants, then Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodonozor with his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects? What the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the Scripture ſoundeth. 1 Pet. 2.17. The Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher and the Scripture tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs to honour Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar. The Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a king to a Father, to a Phiſition, to a Pilot, to a Shepheard. Malach. 1.6 Caeſar is to be honoured as a Father. Eccus. 38.1. to be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                        <p>Our Caeſar is a Phiſition Politicall, and Metaphyſical,</p>
                     </note> ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Iehouah</hi> ſetting vp, not a <hi>dead,</hi> but (as <hi>Menander</hi> calleth the <hi>King</hi>) his <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing</hi> Image, preuaile with all his <hi>godly</hi> Subiects at the ſwéete <hi>harmonie</hi> of the <hi>ſacred Scripture,</hi> ſounding out with Saint <hi>Peter, <hi>Honour the King,</hi>
                     </hi> to giue him that honour which hee hath commaunded? Will you ſée where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> compareth a <hi>King?</hi> will you ſée what <hi>titles</hi> God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a <hi>King?</hi> The Philoſopher com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth a King to a <hi>Father,</hi> to a <hi>Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> to a <hi>Pylot,</hi> to a <hi>Sheepheard.</hi> If I be a <hi>Father,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>where is mine honour?</hi> If I be a <hi>Father,</hi> may the king ſay, <hi>where is mine honour?</hi> Honour <hi>Caeſar</hi> as a <hi>Phiſition:</hi> The Phiſitian de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuering the bodie of man from <hi>euill</hi> humours, and noyſome <hi>diſeaſes,</hi> reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it to <hi>health: Caeſar</hi> deliuereth the <hi>body</hi> of the <hi>eſtate</hi> from <hi>euill</hi> humours, from <hi>daungerous</hi> diſeaſes, preſerueth the ſacred <hi>Cleargie,</hi> the honorable <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie,</hi> the well meaning <hi>Communaltie,</hi> in perfect health. <hi>Caeſar</hi> is not onely a <hi>politicall,</hi> but alſo a <hi>corporall,</hi> and that not a <hi>Phyſicall,</hi> but (that you in <hi>Caeſar</hi>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:152155:50"/>
may ſee an extraordinarie ſtampe of the finger of God) a <hi>Metaphyſicall</hi> ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitian, curing that <hi>euill,</hi> which to the ſkilfulleſt <hi>Chirurgions</hi> is incurable, which one rarely ſkilfull in that ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, firſt not beléeuing, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with his owne eyes often ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he is with the <hi>Wiſe-man</hi> readie to ſay,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 16.12.</note> 
                     <hi>Neither hearbe nor plaiſter hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them.</hi> Wherefore as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſaid of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> expounding his dreame, <hi>Can wee finde ſuch a man:</hi> So we ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her moſt excellent <hi>Maieſtie</hi> by the myraculous <hi>gift</hi> of God healing this <hi>diſeaſe, Can wee finde ſuch a woman as this,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 41.38. To be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a ſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Pilot. An. Dom. 1588. By the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Charles Lord Howard (now Earle of Nottingham) Lord high Admirall of England.</note> 
                     <hi>in whom is the ſpirite of God?</hi> Honour her as a ſkilfull <hi>Pylot,</hi> who notwithſtanding tempeſts by winds from beyond the <hi>Alpes,</hi> and <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Mountaines, notwithſtanding the waues of the Sea haue beene lift vp to heauen, an inuincible <hi>Armada</hi> out of <hi>Caſtile, Portugall, Biſcaie, Andoluſia Arragon, Scicilia, Naples, Sardinia,</hi> the <hi>Baleares,</hi> the <hi>Canaries,</hi> the <hi>Treceras,</hi> the <hi>Indias,</hi> with aſſiſtance of <hi>Rome, Florence, Genua, Malta,</hi> and others deuoted to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> when peace
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152155:50"/>
was pretended, came againſt vs: Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the dreadfull <hi>rocks,</hi> dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous <hi>gulfes,</hi> deuowring <hi>ſands,</hi> hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſwallowing <hi>whirle-pooles</hi> vpon our owne coaſtes,<note place="margin">This the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent age ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mireth, &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie will celebrate. As a good Shepheard. The great Shepheard who redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs by his croſſe, &amp; will crowne her with an incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Crowne, hath brought her from being a Sheepe to the ſlaughter, to be a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard for our ſaluation. Pſal. 23.2. Iudith. 7.8, 12, 31, 14. Howe the Scripture tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs to honor Caeſar.</note> doth ſo ſtill guide vs in a calme, that admiring and amazed wee may ſay, <hi>what man, what woman, what woman more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent than any man, ſo, to the worlds ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration protected, directed, and bleſſed of the Almightie, that windes and ſeas doe ſo obey her, that rockes, that ſhelfes, that ſyrts, that gulfes, that whirle-pooles cannot annoy her?</hi> Haue not the <hi>ſheepe</hi> a reſpectiue regard of the <hi>ſhepheard?</hi> That <hi>flocke</hi> for keeping whereof euer ſince the <hi>great ſhepheard</hi> (for whom ſhe was ſometime <hi>tanquam ouis,</hi> of whom ſhe ſhall receiue an incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible <hi>Crowne</hi> of <hi>glory</hi>) hath giuen her a <hi>hooke,</hi> ſhe hath by moſt vigilant <hi>ſhepheards</hi> made vs reſt in <hi>greene</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, and leadeth vs by (though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a <hi>vaſſall</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi> haue endeauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to cut them off from our <hi>Bethulia</hi>) the <hi>waters</hi> of <hi>comfort.</hi> Will you ſee what <hi>titles</hi> God giueth to a <hi>King?</hi> the title of <hi>Father,</hi> of <hi>Lord,</hi> of <hi>Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:152155:51"/>
of <hi>comforter,</hi> of <hi>annointed</hi> of God, yea all the titles of <hi>honour</hi> in <hi>Heauen</hi> and <hi>Earth.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The people ioyfully. 1 Kinges. 1. 39, 48. Men of warre in the actions moſt reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. 2 Sam. 12.27, 28.</note> God, and man hauing ſo honoured <hi>Caeſar,</hi> let all our <hi>people</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <hi>Caeſar,</hi> as all the people with <hi>ioy</hi> and <hi>muſicall</hi> inſtruments honoured <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon.</hi> Let all <hi>Generals</hi> of armies, ſo honour her, that all be done to her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as <hi>Ioab</hi> fighting againſt <hi>Rabbah</hi> of the children of <hi>Ammon,</hi> and being readie to take the <hi>Citie</hi> of <hi>waters,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The greateſt in acces moſt carefully. Eſter. 5.1, 2.</note> ſent to <hi>Dauid</hi> to come in perſon, that <hi>Dauid,</hi> not <hi>Ioab</hi> might haue the <hi>honour.</hi> Let her be <hi>honoured</hi> with great regard in acceſſe to her <hi>preſence</hi> euen of the <hi>nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> and <hi>deareſt</hi> vnto her,<note place="margin">In preſence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,</note> as <hi>Eſther</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in her royall apparell, ſtood in the <hi>Court</hi> of the <hi>Pallace</hi> vntill the <hi>King</hi> held out the <hi>golden Scepter.</hi> Let her be honoured in her <hi>preſence,</hi> with moſt humble geſture euen of the Miniſters of the eternal God,<note place="margin">1 Kings. 1.23.</note> as <hi>Nathan</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet being come vnto the <hi>King,</hi> made <hi>obeiſance</hi> before the <hi>King</hi> vpon his face to the ground. Let her be <hi>honoured</hi> with gratefull acknowledging of the Lord his vnſpeakable <hi>bleſſinge:</hi> and therefore as <hi>Ioachim</hi> the high <hi>Prieſt,</hi>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:152155:51"/>
and the <hi>auncients</hi> of the children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> ſaid to <hi>Iudeth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging gods bleſſings vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs, all ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerallye are to honour Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</note> for the benefits that God by her had ſhewed to the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> let the <hi>Reuerend Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the truely honourable <hi>Nobilitie</hi> of <hi>England</hi> ſay of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefits which God by her moſt excellent <hi>Maieſtie</hi> hath ſhewed to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Thou art the exaltation of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem: thou art the great glory of Iſrael: thou art the great reioycing of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iudith. 15.8, 9, 10.</note> 
                     <hi>thou haſt done all theſe things by thine hand: thou haſt done much good to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and God is pleaſed there with, bleſſed be thou of the Almightie Lord for euermore, and let all the people ſay,</hi> So be it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Finding that your inſtruction for theſe two,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Feare, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour prepare vs to other duties.</note> 
                     <hi>haue prepared my mind to receiue the reſt, I deſire to know the reſt of my dueties to Caeſar.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>Of them the next is <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> which, ſince it is <hi>vniuſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Obedience.</hi> Not to obey Caeſar, our owne practiſe teach vs to be vniuſt. Ariſtot. in his Oeconom.</note> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of <hi>inferiours,</hi> as the <hi>husband</hi> of the <hi>Wife,</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> of the <hi>ſonne,</hi> the <hi>Maiſter</hi> of the <hi>ſeruant,</hi> and not to giue it to the <hi>Superiour,</hi> euery <hi>Subiect</hi> to his <hi>Soueraigne:</hi> ſince that is true in the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152155:52"/>
eſtate,<note place="margin">Diligent obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, the path to prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Obedience of Subiects, the felicitie of the eſtate. Sophocles in Antig. Then diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience no greater euill Matt. 12.25. Diſobedience ruinateth an eſtate. Titus 3.1. Paule giueth a memorandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to teach obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. 1. Pet. 2.14. Peter comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not only to obey the king, but for the kings ſake the officers of the king. Examples of obedience in the beaſts. Inſecta, be the flies &amp; worms ſuch as bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided in their bodies: as the Bee, the waſp, the Emot, or Piſ-mier, and ſuch like. In the fowles. In all Eſtates. In man. In the celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſpheres. In the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. Pſal. 103.20. In the ſonne of God. Matth. 26, 53. In his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming into the worlde. In his being in the world. In his going out of the world. Iohn. 6.38. Iohn. 4.34. Matth. 26.38 In his agonie manifeſted by his ſweate and his praier. Luk. 22.44. Matth. 26.39.42 44, Obedience actiue and paſsiue.</note> which <hi>Ariſtole</hi> auoucheth in a family, <hi>by how much the more diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any obey, ſo much the greater fauour they finde:</hi> ſince that, as he ſaith, the <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience</hi> of the <hi>Citizens,</hi> is the <hi>felicitie</hi> of the <hi>Citie,</hi> ſince that then their <hi>diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,</hi> as ſaith that Philoſopher, and with him the tragicke Poet, <hi>there is no greater euill:</hi> Since that with it a <hi>houſe</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) cannot ſtand, &amp; a <hi>Kingdome</hi> come to naught: Since that <hi>Paule</hi> for this <hi>duety</hi> would haue a <hi>Memorandum,</hi> ſince <hi>Peter</hi> would haue vs performe this not only to the <hi>King,</hi> but alſo to <hi>ſuch</hi> as are ſent of the <hi>King,</hi> let vs <hi>all</hi> giue all <hi>obedience</hi> to <hi>Ceſar.</hi> But doe <hi>examples</hi> preuaile more then <hi>reaſon?</hi> The whole <hi>worlde</hi> ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth with <hi>examples</hi> of <hi>obedience.</hi> If among the <hi>inſecta</hi> the <hi>Bees</hi> obey their <hi>King:</hi> If among the <hi>beaſts</hi> of the <hi>field,</hi> the <hi>Flockes</hi> follow their <hi>chiefe,</hi> and the <hi>heards</hi> their <hi>head:</hi> If amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>foules</hi> of the ayre, the <hi>Cranes,</hi> when he that wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth ouer them <hi>calleth,</hi> they <hi>come,</hi> when he <hi>flieth</hi> they <hi>follow:</hi> If among <hi>men,</hi> the <hi>ſeruant</hi> obey his <hi>Maiſter,</hi> the <hi>ſonne</hi> his <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Wife</hi> her <hi>Husband:</hi>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:152155:52"/>
If in <hi>man,</hi> the <hi>bodie</hi> obayeth the <hi>ſoule:</hi> If all the <hi>ſpheares</hi> of <hi>Heauen</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their proper and peculiar motions, be circumuolued by the <hi>firſt moueable:</hi> If the <hi>Angels,</hi> which excell in ſtrength bee obedient to the <hi>Commaundementes</hi> of God: If the <hi>Sonne</hi> of God (who could haue had more then twelue <hi>Legions</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi>) performed <hi>obedience,</hi> obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence comming into the <hi>world,</hi> Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence being in the <hi>world,</hi> Obedience going out of the <hi>world:</hi> comming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, <hi>I came downe from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen not to doe mine owne will, but his which hath ſent me:</hi> being in the world <hi>my meate is that I may doe the will of him that ſent me, and finiſh his worke:</hi> going out of the world, when <hi>his ſoule was verie heauie, euen vnto the death,</hi> when <hi>his ſweate was like droppes</hi> of <hi>bloud, trickling downe to the ground</hi> when his <hi>praier</hi> was once, and <hi>againe,</hi> and <hi>againe: Oh my father, if it be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble let this cup paſſe from me, neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe not as I will, but as thou wilt:</hi> Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the <hi>law,</hi> by <hi>fulfilling</hi> it, Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the <hi>croſſe,</hi> by <hi>ſuffering</hi> it. Being
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152155:53"/>
compaſſed with ſuch a cloud of <hi>exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The ende of theſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Obey Caeſar readyly, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.</note> let vs caſt off all <hi>impediments,</hi> and obey all that <hi>Caeſar</hi> commaunds vs. Let vs obey <hi>Caeſar</hi> readylie, obey <hi>ſyncerely,</hi> obey <hi>generally,</hi> obey earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Obey <hi>readily, Dauid</hi> did but ſay to <hi>Ahimelech,</hi> and <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> who will go downe with me? and <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> ſaid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.6.</note> I will goe downe with thee. Obey <hi>ſyncerely,</hi> for that which Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith to <hi>ſeruants,</hi> I may well ſay to <hi>ſubiects, be obedient to them not with eye ſeruice as men pleaſures,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col. 3.22.</note> 
                     <hi>but in ſinglenes of heart fearing God.</hi> Obey <hi>generally,</hi> not what likes vs, but what pleaſeth <hi>Caeſar</hi> to commannd vs: for that which the <hi>Reubenites,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioſua. 1.16.</note> and others ſaid to <hi>Ioſua,</hi> we muſt ſay to <hi>Caeſar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Earneſtly.</note> 
                     <hi>all that thou haſt commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs we will doe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 31.6.</note> 
                     <hi>and whether ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thou ſendeſt vs, wee will goe.</hi> Obey <hi>earneſtly,</hi> as <hi>Iacob</hi> profeſſed, hee hath ſerued <hi>Laban</hi> with all his <hi>might:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Philip. 2.8.</note> and as <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith of <hi>Chriſt, hee became obedient vnto the death.</hi> To <hi>Caeſar</hi> giue this <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> this obedience thou oweſt to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:152155:53"/>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Is not <hi>tribute</hi> to the <hi>throne</hi> of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the next <hi>dutie</hi> which I owe to <hi>Caeſar?</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>When I conſider that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie times <hi>Caeſars eye lids</hi> doe not <hi>ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> that our eyes may ſafely <hi>ſleepe:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tribute.</note> that <hi>Caeſars <hi>ſworde</hi>
                     </hi> cutteth off <hi>theeues,</hi> that Subiects may enioy their <hi>goods:</hi> that <hi>Caeſars Scepter</hi> curbeth <hi>Adulterers,</hi> that wee may kéepe our <hi>wiues,</hi> our <hi>daughters,</hi> our <hi>maidens</hi> in <hi>chaſtity:</hi> that <hi>Caeſars gouernment</hi> is our ſafe-conduct to paſſe the <hi>high wayes, wide heathes, thicke woods, wilde mountaines</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger, either to our purſes, from théeus, or our liues from Cut-throats:<note place="margin">Benefits from Caeſar.</note> that <hi>Caeſars royall Nauie at Sea,</hi> and mightie Forces to <hi>Caeſars</hi> great expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſometimes at <hi>home,</hi> ſometimes <hi>abroad,</hi> beat of the <hi>Enemie</hi> from inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our <hi>Land,</hi> waſting our <hi>Countrey,</hi> ſpoyling our <hi>goods,</hi> rifling our <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> burning our <hi>houſes,</hi> ſacking our <hi>Citties,</hi> deflouring our <hi>Daughters,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing our <hi>wiues,</hi> daſhing out the brains of our tender <hi>Babes,</hi> tormenting our ſelues with <hi>cruell death,</hi> taking away from vs the <hi>worde of God,</hi> which as
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152155:54"/>
                     <hi>Elies</hi> daughter in law ſaid of the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Arke of God,<note place="margin">1. Salm. 4.22.</note> 
                     <hi>would be the departure of glorie from Iſrael:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat, 12.34.</note> my tongue cannot but out of the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of my heart ſpeake of the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne <hi>miniſter of God</hi> among vs, as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> hath before ſpoken from <hi>God</hi> himſelfe for the <hi>miniſters</hi> of his Church,<note place="margin">Equitie.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.7.8.</note> 
                     <hi>VVho goeth a warfare at anie time at his owne coſt? who planteth a Vineyard, and eateth not of the fruite thereof? or who feedeth a flocke, and eateth not of the milke of the flocke?</hi> If <hi>Dauid</hi> entering into a ſerious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Gods benefits beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.12.</note> breaketh out into this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Others gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitie.</note> 
                     <hi>VVhat ſhall I render vnto the Lord for all his benefites towards me?</hi> If the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſo ſoone as <hi>Ioſua</hi> had diuided vnto them the <hi>Cities</hi> which the Lord had giuen them, preſently gaue <hi>Ioſua</hi> an inheritance, a <hi>Citie</hi> for an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,<note place="margin">Ioſ. 19.49, 50.</note> a <hi>Citie</hi> which himſelfe woulde craue,<note place="margin">Eccles. 1.7.</note> euen <hi>Timnah-ſerah in mount E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim:</hi> If <hi>riuers</hi> goe out of the place whence they returne and goe: if the <hi>earth</hi> receyuing ſeed, returneth a crop: O my <hi>ſonne</hi> are our hearts like to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:152155:54"/>
heart, are not the <hi>Engliſh</hi> more vnthankfull then the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> more vnnaturall then the <hi>waters,</hi> more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull then the <hi>earth,</hi> If in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of theſe infinite benefits, which they dayly receyue from <hi>Caeſars throne,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Cor. 9.7.</note> they be not euer moſt willing, and that with chearefulneſſe (for as <hi>God,</hi> ſo ſurely Gods <hi>Vicegerent</hi> loueth a <hi>chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full giuer</hi>) to returne <hi>tribute,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Neceſsitie of tribute.</note> which <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero</hi> calleth the <hi>ſinewes</hi> of war, which <hi>Vlpianus</hi> calleth the <hi>ſinewes</hi> of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, without which there was neuer, that any part of the Scripture can ſhow, any well ordered ſtate, as a <hi>pledge</hi> of our thankfull hearts to the <hi>throne</hi> of <hi>Caeſar?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The will of God. Rom. 13.7. Expreſſed in his word.</note> If thou wilt ſee what is commaunded, the bleſſed <hi>Apoſtle</hi> he ſayth, <hi>Giue to all men their dutie, tribute to whom ye owe tribute,</hi> and that yee may know to whom ye owe it, of this eſpecially (I call to witneſſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.21. Mark. 12.17. Luke. 20.25.</note> S. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> Saint <hi>Marke,</hi> and Saint <hi>Luke</hi>) the Lord Ieſus ſaith, <hi>Giue to Caeſar thoſe things which be Caeſars:</hi> Is any ſo wicked to detaine this? To take from a <hi>priuate</hi> man it is theft, to take from the church it is <hi>ſacriledge,</hi> to take, or
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152155:55"/>
detaine from the <hi>Prince,</hi> it is <hi>peculatus,</hi> robbing of the common <hi>treaſure,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The greatnes of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence Prou. 28.24. who detain it.</note> the common treaſure to bee imployed to common <hi>good.</hi> He ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> that robbeth his <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>mother,</hi> and ſaith it is no <hi>tranſgreſſion,</hi> is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of a man that deſtroyeth: He, may any man ſay, that detaineth <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute,</hi> or other <hi>duties</hi> from <hi>Caeſar,</hi> being the <hi>father</hi> or <hi>mother</hi> of his Countrey,<note place="margin">Examples of God.</note> and ſaith it is no tranſgreſſion, <hi>is the companion of a man that deſtroyeth his Countrey.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod 30.14.</note> Are we ſo vnreaſonable that without examples we yéeld not to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? Before there was any king in <hi>Iſrael</hi> to take <hi>tribute,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dauid.</note> the Lord himſelfe tooke a <hi>tribute:</hi> when they had kings, the flowers of all their kings,<note place="margin">2 Sam, 20.24. 1 Kings. 4.6. Salomon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring it. Examples of the people of God. Nehemiah. 5.4. Of the bleſſed Virgin.</note> had for their <hi>tribute</hi> a peculier <hi>Office: Dauid</hi> the paterne of deuotion, ouer the <hi>tribute</hi> ſet <hi>Adoram: Salomon</hi> the myrror of <hi>VViſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> placed ouer the <hi>tribute, Adoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram:</hi> when they were vnder the kings of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> there were amongſt the people of God, that vpon their <hi>landes,</hi> and their <hi>vineyards,</hi> borrowed money for the kings <hi>tribute.</hi> When the bleſſed <hi>virgin</hi> was verie great by the holie
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:152155:55"/>
Ghoſt, with the <hi>Sauiour</hi> of our ſoules, in the depth of winter ſhee tranailed from <hi>Nazareth</hi> in <hi>Galile,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc. 2.4, 5, 6.</note> to <hi>Bethlem</hi> in <hi>Iudah,</hi> to performe this dutie to the vnder Officers of a <hi>Lieutenant</hi> to an heathen <hi>prince.</hi> When the ſonne of <hi>God</hi> conuerſing with the ſonnes of <hi>men,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 17.24, 25, 26, 27.</note> 
                     <hi>Peter</hi> was aſked if he paid not <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute,</hi> he taking tribute of an vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable creature, that <hi>tribute</hi> for <hi>him</hi> and <hi>peter</hi> might be paid, bound all the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable men,<note place="margin">Of the Sonne of God pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, though to paye it wrought a miracle, may mooue euery one to the perfourmance of this dutie.</note> though they doe it with their great difficultie, to performe this dutie to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Wherefore I conclude this poynt with Saint <hi>Ambroſe, <hi>Si cenſum filius Dei ſoluit, quis tu tantus es qui non putas eſſe ſoluendum?</hi> If the ſonne of God paid <hi>tribute</hi> or <hi>ſubſidie,</hi> who ſo <hi>great a man</hi> art thou, which thinkeſt it not to be paid?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Before you enter into your ſpeech of <hi>defence,</hi>
                     </hi>
                     <note place="margin">Defence.</note> 
                     <hi>I deſire to heare ſome <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement</hi> to this dutie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>To encourage vs in this dutie (wherein whoſo through daſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, or any other vile reſpect fayleth,<note place="margin">Puniſhments of Daſtardie amongeſt the Romanes.</note> I wiſh him baniſhed either into <hi>Italie,</hi> whoſe glorie the auncient <hi>Romanes</hi>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:152155:56"/>
condemned ſuch wretches neuer to eat their meat but ſtanding,<note place="margin">Tranſiluani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> and herevnto bound them by oath: or to the <hi>Tranſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Thoſe of that countrey of Dacia.</note> whoſe predeceſſours the <hi>Daci</hi> inioyned them ſeruile ſubiection to their owne wiues, and to ſleepe with their heades euer towardes the beddes féete: Or to that part of <hi>Greece</hi> where ſometime dwelt the <hi>Spartanes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Spartans.</note> who ordayned that their cloathes ſhould be rent, their Beardes euer halfe cut, permitted euerie man to ſtrike them without penaltie, but accompted it a great diſgrace to match in their ſtocke)</p>
                  <p>To encourage vs to this dutie, let vs conſider her <hi>Maieſties confidence</hi> in <hi>God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to this dutie.</note> Gods <hi>encouragement</hi> to her <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,</hi> the <hi>confuſion</hi> of her <hi>enemies,</hi> the <hi>thankeſgiuing</hi> befitting <hi>England.</hi> Her Maieſties confidence in God, <hi>The Lord is my rock and my fortreſſe, and he that deliuereth me: God is my ſtrength, and in him will I truſt, my Shield and the horne of my ſaluation,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Sam, 22.2.3</note> 
                     <hi>my high tower, my refuge, my Sauiour, thou haſt ſaued me from violence.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Caeſars con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in God.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Gods <hi>encouragement</hi> to her <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152155:56"/>
Be ſtrong, and of a good courage:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gods incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to Caeſar. Ioſua. 1.6.</note> The <hi>confuſion</hi> of her <hi>foes,</hi> whither for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine inuading her Dominions, or conſpiring at home, but confounded from heauen: That as,<note place="margin">The confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Caeſars foes.</note> 
                     <hi>Heliodorus</hi> told the King <hi>Seleucus</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> they may tell their <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of her <hi>Maieſtie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Mac. 3.38.39.</note> 
                     <hi>If thou haſt any enemie or Traitour, ſende him thither, and thou ſhalt receiue him wel ſcourged, if he eſcape with his life: For in that place no doubt is a ſpeciall power of God, for he that dwelleth in heauen hath his eye on that place, and defendeth it, and he beateth and deſtroyeth them that come to hurt it.</hi> The <hi>thankeſgiuing</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> now well befitteth <hi>England,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing now befitting England.</note> 
                     <hi>If the Lord himſelfe had not beene on our ſide, may <hi>Iſrael</hi> now ſay, if the Lord had not beene on our ſide, when men roſe vp againſt vs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 124.</note> 
                     <hi>they then had ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vs vp quicke, when their wrath was kindled againſt vs: the waters had drowned vs, and the ſtreame had gone ouer our ſoule: then had the ſwelling waters gone ouer our ſoule: praiſed be the Lord which hath not giuen vs a praie vnto their teeth, our ſoule is eſcaped as
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152155:57"/>
a bird out of the ſnare of the Fowler, the ſnare is broken, &amp; weare deliuered, our helpe is in the name of the Lord which hath made heauen &amp; earth.</hi> Therefore I ſpeak not to the alone,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.7.</note> but as the true louer of ſoules, ſaith, <hi>I charge you O daughters of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> by the Roes &amp; by the Hindes of the field, that you ſtirre not vp nor waken my loue vntill ſhe pleaſe:</hi> ſo I charge you (my <hi>duety</hi> to my <hi>God,</hi> my <hi>duety</hi> to his <hi>Church,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Adiiura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</note> my <hi>duty</hi> to my <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> together with my deſire of the ſafety of your ſelues, and the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your ſoules enforceth me this to charge you) <hi>I charge you O ſonnes &amp; daughters of the ſupernal <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> by the ioyes of Heauen,</hi> as euer you would enioy them: <hi>by the paines of Hell,</hi> as euer you would auoide them:<note place="margin">Gal. 4.26.</note> 
                     <hi>by the pretious bloud of the Sonne of God,</hi> as euer therein you would be waſhed from your ſinnes, <hi>by the bleſſed fauour of the eternal Father,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">to reueale forraine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plots. 2 Kings. 68.9.12.</note> as euer you would ſee his face: If you know of any <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Aram,</hi> taking counſell with his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants agninſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> if <hi>God</hi> by any meanes reueale it vnto you, that you would with <hi>Eliſeus</hi> make knowen to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:152155:57"/>
our <hi>Caeſar,</hi> euen the words that the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Aram</hi> ſpeaketh in his priuie <hi>Chamber:</hi> If any <hi>Bigthan</hi> and <hi>Tereſh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">To detect do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies. Eſter. 2.21, 22.</note> ſeeke to lay hands on our <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> that you would preſently with <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docheus,</hi> and <hi>Eſter</hi> certifie our <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne:</hi> If your ſeruice be fitting,<note place="margin">To performe all dutifull ſeruice. 1. Sam. 10.26. Carefull to guard her Maieſtie. 1. Sam. 26.15, 16.</note> that wherſoeuer <hi>ſhe</hi> goe, <hi>yee</hi> attend <hi>her,</hi> as that <hi>band</hi> of men did <hi>Saul,</hi> whoſe heart God had touched: that when <hi>ſhe</hi> reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>ye</hi> keepe <hi>her,</hi> that <hi>none</hi> that be <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> to hurt her, come neere the Lords <hi>annointed,</hi> leaſt as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> it be ſaid to you, <hi>yee be worthy to die, becauſe ye haue not kept the Lords</hi> annointed: That if ye ſee any <hi>appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of <hi>perill,</hi> you with <hi>Dauids</hi> men,<note place="margin">To preuent all perill. 2 Sam. 21.17 2 Sam. 18.3.</note> and with the true hearted people, be carefull that <hi>ſhe being worth ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of vs,</hi> come not into any <hi>perill:</hi> If in the leaſt <hi>diſtreſſe</hi> (the <hi>Lord</hi> keepe her from all <hi>diſtreſſe</hi>) her <hi>ſoule</hi> deſireth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, that may preſerue <hi>her,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">To prouide whatſoeuer may preſerue her.</note> that you would with all <hi>alacritie</hi> prouide it as the three <hi>mightie</hi> euen with the <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard</hi> of their liues, brake into the <hi>hoſte</hi> of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.15, 16.</note> and drew <hi>water</hi> out of the <hi>Well</hi> of <hi>Bethelem</hi> and brought
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152155:58"/>
it to <hi>Dauid:</hi> If any with <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ibenob</hi> thinke (my touge faultreth in pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the word,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 21.16, 17. To deſtroy all that would aſſault her. An aſſertion of aſſiſtance. Iudges. 5.20, 21. Iudges. 5.15, 18. Prediction of honour to all true Serui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours. Iudges. 4.14, 15, 16. and 5.12, 15. Eſpecially the cheefe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunders. 5.16, 17. But of diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the negligent, And verſe 23. of a curſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God himſelfe vppon obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>e Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours in this point,</note> and the Lord confound them that entertaine any ſuch entent) to ſlay <hi>Dauid;</hi> That with <hi>Abiſhai</hi> ye prſently though with expoſinge your <hi>bodies</hi> to <hi>perill</hi> to keepe <hi>her</hi> ſacred <hi>body</hi> from all <hi>perill,</hi> ſucour <hi>Dauid</hi> and ſmite them that <hi>ſo</hi> preſume and <hi>kill</hi> them. And know that as the <hi>Starrs of Heauen</hi> fought againſt <hi>Siſera in theire order</hi> and the <hi>Riuer</hi> of <hi>Kiſhon</hi> ſwepte them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie, ſo <hi>Heauen</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> and all the <hi>creatures</hi> in them both, ſhall <hi>fight</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and <hi>ſweepe</hi> away <hi>her</hi> enemies. If any <hi>loially</hi> ſerue vnder <hi>Debora,</hi> their memorie with <hi>Iſſachars, Zebulus</hi> and <hi>Nepthalis</hi> ſhalbe <hi>honourable:</hi> If any be a <hi>valient generall</hi> againſt <hi>her</hi> eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, his <hi>honour</hi> with <hi>Barakes</hi> ſhalbe <hi>eternized:</hi> If any be <hi>backwarde</hi> they with <hi>Ruben, Gilliad, Dan</hi> and <hi>Aſher</hi> ſhall be <hi>branded</hi> with <hi>diſhonour:</hi> If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with <hi>Meroz</hi> cannot be drawen to take opportunitie to aſſiſt <hi>Debora</hi> and the <hi>Lord</hi> in <hi>Debora,</hi> let them looke for the <hi>curſſe</hi> giuen to <hi>Meroz,</hi> not a <hi>curſſe</hi> onely from <hi>Debora,</hi> but a <hi>curſſe</hi> from
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152155:58"/>
the <hi>Lord,</hi> the <hi>Lord,</hi> who willeth you to <hi>bleſſe</hi> them that <hi>curſſe</hi> you, not by <hi>man,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 5.44. Luke. 6.28. may drawe vs Iudges. 5.23. to this duty.</note> but by his <hi>Angels</hi> willeth to curſſe <hi>Meroz,</hi> for not aſſiſting the <hi>Lord,</hi> for not aſſiſting the <hi>Lord</hi> againſt the <hi>mightie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deare <hi>Father,</hi> with many thanks for your paines in the <hi>former,</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to ſpeake of <hi>Prayer</hi> which you reſerued to the <hi>laſt.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>To the <hi>laſt</hi> I reſerued <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> for <hi>Caeſar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prayer.</note> not as the <hi>leaſt,</hi> but as the <hi>greateſt</hi> of our <hi>dueties</hi> to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prayer the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent of our duties to Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</note> The other be intended wholly to the <hi>King,</hi> this is directed immediatly vnto <hi>God. Feare,</hi> is in regard of the ſword: <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Crowne: Obede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> in regard of the <hi>Scepter: Tribute,</hi> to the <hi>Throne: defence,</hi> to the <hi>perſon:</hi> But <hi>Prayer,</hi> to the <hi>founder,</hi> protector,<note place="margin">To feare of the ſworde, 2 Sam. 1.22.21.</note> and <hi>director</hi> of <hi>Caeſar. Sauls</hi> ſword ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer returned emptie from the <hi>bloud</hi> of of the ſlaine, and the <hi>fall</hi> of the <hi>mightie,</hi> as yet was the <hi>ſhield</hi> of the <hi>mightie</hi> caſt downe. The <hi>ſhield</hi> of <hi>Saul</hi> as though he had not beene <hi>annointed</hi> with <hi>oyle.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts. 12 21, 22.23. To honor of the crowne.</note> 
                     <hi>Herod</hi> (whom <hi>Ioſephus</hi> ſtill calleth <hi>Agrippa</hi>) was honoured, when arayed
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:152155:59"/>
in <hi>royall</hi> apparell, ſitting in the <hi>Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> ſeate, making an <hi>Oration,</hi> the people ſhowted, <hi>the voyce of God, and not of man,</hi> yet imediately the <hi>Angell</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> ſmote him bycauſe he gaue not <hi>glory</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> ſo that he was eaten of <hi>wormes</hi> and gaue vp the <hi>Ghoſt. Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuerus</hi> had a golden <hi>Scepter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Obedience to the ſcripture. Heſter. 11.5, 2</note> and was obeyed from <hi>India</hi> euen to <hi>Ethiopia</hi> in <hi>127. prouinces,</hi> yet godly Queene <hi>Heſter</hi> had no pleaſure in his <hi>feaſt,</hi> and dranke no <hi>wine</hi> of his <hi>drinke</hi> offerings. How was the <hi>throne</hi> of <hi>Nabuchodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nozor</hi> ſupported with <hi>Tribute,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tribute to the throne.</note> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the aboundant charges of his <hi>houſe,</hi> and the exceſſiue expences of his <hi>Armies</hi> made an <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>gould</hi> whoſe <hi>breadth</hi> was <hi>6.</hi> whoſe height was <hi>60.</hi> Cubits?<note place="margin">Dan. 3.1.</note> yet was he driuen from <hi>men,</hi> and did eate graſſe as the <hi>Oxen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">4.30.</note> and his <hi>bodie</hi> was wet with the <hi>dew</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> till his <hi>haires</hi> were growen as the <hi>Eagles</hi> feathers, &amp; his nayles like <hi>birds</hi> clawes.<note place="margin">Defence to the perſon. Mat. 9.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 28.</note> 
                     <hi>Antiochus</hi> defended with his Armies, ſwelled with pride, breathed out fier in his rage againſt the <hi>Iewes,</hi> thought hee might commaunde the <hi>floudes</hi> of the <hi>ſea,</hi> weigh the <hi>moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:152155:59"/>
in the <hi>ballance,</hi> reach the <hi>Starres</hi> of <hi>heauen,</hi> yet was hee ſmot with an incureable and inuiſible <hi>plague,</hi> the <hi>wormes</hi> came out of the <hi>bodie</hi> of this <hi>wicked</hi> man in aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, whiles he was yet aliue, his <hi>fleſh</hi> fell off for paine and torment, and all his <hi>armie</hi> was grieued at his <hi>ſmell:</hi> and notwithſtanding his <hi>proteſtation</hi> concerning <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> concerning the <hi>Iewes,</hi> concerning the <hi>Temple,</hi> the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <hi>Veſſels,</hi> the <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> and his owne <hi>conuerſion,</hi> (wherein O howe <hi>ſhineth</hi> the <hi>triumph</hi> of the <hi>Deitie?</hi>) He died a miſerable <hi>death</hi> in a ſtrange <hi>Countrey</hi> among the <hi>Mountaines.</hi> So <hi>little</hi> doe <hi>feare</hi> of the <hi>ſword, honour</hi> of the <hi>crown, Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Scepter, Tribute</hi> to the <hi>Throne, Defence</hi> to the <hi>perſon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Without praier to the Inthroner make not Caeſar happy.</note> preuaile to <hi>Caeſars</hi> happineſſe without <hi>Prayer</hi> to the <hi>inthroner</hi> and <hi>preſeruer</hi> of <hi>Caeſar. Prayer</hi> therefore, my <hi>Son, Praier</hi> which ſpringeth from the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> it ſelfe ſayth <hi>Paule,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Whence prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſpringeth. Rom. 8.26.</note> 
                     <hi>maketh requeſts for vs with ſighes which cannot bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. Praier,</hi> which is the <hi>Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> of the <hi>faithfull ſoule</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>prayer</hi> of him that <hi>humbleth</hi> himſelfe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:152155:60"/>
ſayth the ſonne of <hi>Sirac, goeth through the cloudes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ecclus. 35.17. What prayer affecteth. That prayer excelleth. Apoc. 8.3. 1. Tim. 2.1. Prayer wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto Paul be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all things Exhorteth for all men generally. 1. Tim. 2.2. He exhorteth for kings ſpecially.</note> 
                     <hi>and ceaſeth not till it come neere, and will not depart vntill the moſt high haue reſpect thereunto. Prayer,</hi> which is the <hi>odours</hi> in the <hi>golden violl</hi> offered vpon the <hi>golden Aultar,</hi> which is before the <hi>Throne: Prayer</hi> wherevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth <hi>Chriſtians</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all <hi>duties: Prayer</hi> were vnto hee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth <hi>generally</hi> for all men, he exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>ſpecially</hi> for <hi>Kings: Specially</hi> for <hi>Kings</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>greatneſſe</hi> of the <hi>cares</hi> which they take, in reſpect of the <hi>perils</hi> whereto they bee ſubiect, in reſpect of the <hi>difficultie</hi> in deſtribution of <hi>rewards</hi> and <hi>puniſhments,</hi> in reſpect of the aboundant <hi>good</hi> which diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from them to the whole <hi>eſtate. Prayer</hi> for <hi>Kings,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In reſpect of the cares which they take. Heſter 6.1 In reſpect of the perils whereto they be ſubiect.</note> in reſpect of the <hi>cares</hi> they take: In the greateſt <hi>Dominion,</hi> ſaith <hi>Saluſt</hi>) there is the <hi>greateſt care,</hi> through <hi>this</hi> the <hi>Kings</hi> ſleepe departeth from <hi>him.</hi> In reſpect of the <hi>perils</hi> to the which they are <hi>ſubiect,</hi> becauſe in the <hi>Prince,</hi> the enimie <hi>hath Nero</hi> his <hi>wiſh,</hi> all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>heads</hi> of the <hi>people</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one <hi>bodie,</hi> like the king of <hi>Aram,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. King. 22.31.</note> the <hi>Enemie</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth his <hi>captaines</hi> to fight onelie
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:152155:60"/>
againſt the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <p>In reſpect of the difficultie in the deſerts, right beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in rewards and inflicting of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. 1. King. 3.9. In reſpect of the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant good that deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from the Soueraigne to the whole Eſtate. The Sunne in the world, our Soueraigne in her Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſtie. Pray for Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</p>
                        <p>For Caeſar ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Ezra. 6.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
                        <p>For Caeſar eſteemeth of thy prayer.</p>
                     </note> In reſpect of the <hi>difficultie</hi> of the right beſtowing <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes</hi> and inflicting of <hi>puniſhments</hi> there beeing (heauen alone being free from all corruption) ſmooth <hi>Abſolons</hi> dogged <hi>Doegs,</hi> blacke mothed <hi>Shimeis,</hi> bloudie handed <hi>Ioabs,</hi> falſe hearted <hi>Sibas,</hi> ſhameleſſe <hi>harlots.</hi> So that <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and all for <hi>Salomon</hi> had neede to <hi>pray.</hi> For who is able to iudge this <hi>mighty</hi> people? In reſpect of the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant <hi>good</hi> which deſcendeth from the <hi>royal Maieſtie</hi> to the whole <hi>eſtate:</hi> for as the <hi>Sunne</hi> is a reſemblance of the <hi>Deity</hi> in the <hi>frame</hi> of this <hi>world,</hi> giuing <hi>light, heat, life</hi> to all things: ſo the <hi>Soueraigne</hi> of euerie <hi>eſtate,</hi> is a <hi>pattern</hi> of the great <hi>God,</hi> from whome our whole <hi>eſtates, lawes</hi> to liue by, and <hi>comfort</hi> in our ſeuerall <hi>courſes</hi> doe proceed. <hi>pray</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſince <hi>Caeſar</hi> needes thy prayer. <hi>Pray</hi> for <hi>Caeſar,</hi> for as <hi>Darius</hi> highly reſpected the <hi>Sacrifices</hi> and <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> of the <hi>prieſts</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for his life, and for his <hi>ſonnes:</hi> ſo her moſt <hi>graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Maieſtie</hi> greatly regardeth that <hi>prayer</hi> bee made for <hi>her,</hi> by her tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-chriſtian <hi>ſubiects.</hi> And let <hi>ſubiects</hi>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:152155:61"/>
pray for <hi>Caeſar:</hi> ſince <hi>prayer</hi> is <hi>honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, prayer</hi> is <hi>eaſie, praier</hi> is <hi>profitable prayer</hi> is <hi>honourable,</hi> If wee account it a grace vnto vs to follow the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions</hi> of the greateſt perſons on <hi>earth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">For prayer is honourable. Reue. 8.8, 9, 10, 11. For prayer is eaſie.</note> O howe great <hi>honour</hi> will it be for vs to imitate the <hi>bleſſed</hi> ſpirits in <hi>heauen? Prayer</hi> is <hi>eaſie,</hi> if thy <hi>purſe</hi> bee ſo <hi>poore,</hi> that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>pay</hi> no <hi>tribute</hi> to <hi>Caeſar:</hi> if thy <hi>body</hi> be ſo <hi>feeble,</hi> that it can do <hi>nothing</hi> for the <hi>defence</hi> of <hi>Caeſar:</hi> yet if thy <hi>hart</hi> be not too <hi>lewd,</hi> too <hi>wicked:</hi> if thy <hi>heart</hi> be not <hi>voyde</hi> of all <hi>pietie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">For prayer is profitable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities. Ionah, 2.1, 7, 10. Act. 12.5, 7, 8, 9, 10. Tobit. 3.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. Againſt ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Ecclus. 38.9— 2 King. 20.3, 5.6. Againſt death. Againſt the enemies.</note> 
                     <hi>voide</hi> of all <hi>Chriſtian dutie:</hi> thy heart wil daily and often euery day pray for <hi>Caeſar. Prayer</hi> is <hi>profitable,</hi> profitable againſt all <hi>cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,</hi> it deliuered <hi>Ionas</hi> out of the <hi>Whales</hi> bellie, <hi>Peter</hi> out of <hi>priſon, Sara</hi> the daughter of <hi>Raguel</hi> from <hi>reproach: profitable</hi> againſt <hi>ſickneſſe,</hi> for (ſayth the <hi>ſonne</hi> of <hi>Sirac</hi>) my <hi>ſonne faile not in thy ſickneſſe, but pray vnto the Lord, and he will make thee whole:</hi> profitable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt death, <hi>It prolonged Ezechias life fifteene yeares:</hi> profitable <hi>againſt the enemies,</hi> againſt the enemies, this, but without <hi>this,</hi> againſt <hi>vs,</hi> the <hi>enemies</hi> preuaile: when <hi>Moyſes</hi> lift vp his
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:152155:61"/>
hand, <hi>Iſrael</hi> preuailed:<note place="margin">Exod. 17.11. If Paule com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to pray for Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, 1 Tim. 22. Baruch. 1.11. Ierem. 29.7. If Baruch and Ieremie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to pray for Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchodono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor.</note> but when <hi>he</hi> let his hand downe, <hi>Amaleck</hi> preuailed: if <hi>Paule</hi> exhorted and commanded to pray for <hi>Nero</hi> a man ſo wicked that he murdered his <hi>Tutor,</hi> his <hi>mother,</hi> and was natures <hi>Monſter:</hi> If the <hi>prophets</hi> commaunded the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to pray for the life of the <hi>king</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who had waſted <hi>Iudea</hi> with <hi>ſword</hi> and <hi>fire,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged and taken <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> burned the <hi>Temple,</hi> caried away the <hi>holy veſſels,</hi> ſet fire on the whole <hi>citie,</hi> brake downe the walles of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> round about,<note place="margin">2. King. 24, and 25. chap.</note> 
                     <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered</hi> many people, <hi>caried</hi> others to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſeruitude, <hi>ſlue</hi> the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of the <hi>king</hi> before his <hi>eies,</hi> pulled out his <hi>eies,</hi> bound him in <hi>chaines,</hi> carried him to <hi>Babel,</hi> and as if to <hi>murder</hi> the <hi>innocent,</hi> to <hi>rauiſh</hi> the <hi>chaſte,</hi> to carrie <hi>princes</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>captiuitie,</hi> to <hi>ſacke</hi> the <hi>holy Citie,</hi> to <hi>burne</hi> the <hi>Temple</hi> of the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>heauen,</hi> were not <hi>impietie</hi> inough, that hee might come to the full <hi>height</hi> of all <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie:</hi> he ſet vp a <hi>golden Image,</hi> and by a <hi>Herauld</hi> proclaimed that whoſoeuer did not <hi>worſhip</hi> it,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.1, 4, 5, 6.</note> ſhould bee caſt into the midſt of a hot fierie <hi>fornace:</hi> If the holie <hi>Prophet</hi> commaunded the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:152155:62"/>
to pray for wicked <hi>Nabuchodono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Peter. 1.21. What woulde the holye ghoſt that we ſhould do for Elizabeth? The royall acts of Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, Dauid, Salomon, Aſa, and Ioſiah. performed by her Maieſtie. 1. Chro. 16.4, 5:6, 7, 37, 38, 39. 1 King. 15, 13 2 King. 23.1, 2.3. 1. King. 6 That which one ſaid of Salomon, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie haue ſaide of Elizabeth. 1. Kin. 10 8, 9 That which the ſtraunger Iewes ſaid of the Apoſtles, hauing recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the holy Ghoſt, we can not but ſay of our miniſters in the dayes of Elizabeth.</note> what would that <hi>holy ſpirit,</hi> by whom both the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did write, that all <hi>Engliſh,</hi> all <hi>Iriſh,</hi> all others vnder the <hi>ſubiection,</hi> or <hi>protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of her moſt gracious <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> ſhould doe for <hi>Queene Elizabeth,</hi> who whereas <hi>Auguſtus</hi> ſaid he found <hi>Rome</hi> of <hi>Bricke,</hi> but left it of <hi>Marble,</hi> may ſay <hi>ſhee</hi> found <hi>England</hi> of <hi>Braſſe</hi> and <hi>Lead,</hi> but brought it to <hi>Siluer</hi> &amp; <hi>Golde,</hi> with <hi>Dauid</hi> appoynted the <hi>Leuites</hi> to ſing in their courſes, with <hi>Aſa</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed <hi>Idols.</hi> with <hi>Ioſiah</hi> reſtored the <hi>Booke</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> with <hi>Salomon</hi> buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a <hi>Temple</hi> to the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Heauen.</hi> So that as the Queene of <hi>Saba</hi> ſayd of <hi>Salomon,</hi> manie haue ſayd of <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, Happie are thy men, happie are theſe thy ſeruants that ſtand before thee, and heare thy wiſedome. Bleſſed bee the Lorde thy God, which loued thee, to ſet thee on the throne of Iſrael, becauſe the Lord loued Iſrael for euer, and made the Queene to do equitie and righteouſnes.</hi> Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> returning from <hi>forraine coaſtes,</hi> may ſay of the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> of their <hi>Countries</hi> in the daies of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:152155:62"/>
her Maieſtie, as thoſe <hi>ſtranger-Iewes,</hi> did of <hi>the Apoſtles</hi> hauing receiued the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Acts. 2.11.</note> 
                     <hi>we heard them ſpeake in our owne tongues, the wonderful works of God.</hi> Shall we not <hi>pray</hi> for ſuch a <hi>Queene?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.2, 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Pray</hi> for her (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) in reſpect of <hi>your ſelues,</hi> &amp; in reſpect <hi>of God.</hi> In reſpect of your ſelues,<note place="margin">Pray for her in reſpect of your ſelues. 1. Tim. 2.2. That you may liue a quiet, and a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able life, in all godlineſſe, Gen. 28, 16, 17</note> 
                     <hi>that you may liue a quiet &amp; a peaceable life in all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and honeſtie.</hi> A quiet life, <hi>that we haue no inſurrections at home:</hi> a peaceable life, <hi>that we haue no inuaſion from abroad:</hi> In all godlines, that it may be ſaid of <hi>England</hi> as <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid of <hi>Bethel, Surely the Lord is in this place, this is none other, but the houſe of God, &amp; this is the gate of heauen:</hi> And in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie,<note place="margin">And in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie. Rom. 2.24.</note> 
                     <hi>that the name of the Lord be not blaſphemed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Gentiles,</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Mahumitans</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Romiſh Recuſants</hi> through you, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>your light may ſo ſhine before men that they may ſee your good workes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matt. 5.16.</note> 
                     <hi>and glorifie your father which is in heauen,</hi> as ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>that they which ſpeake euil of you as of euill doers, may by your good workes which they ſhall ſee,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.12.</note> 
                     <hi>glorifie God in the day of the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:152155:63"/>
viſitation.</hi> In reſpect of <hi>God</hi> our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pray for Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar in reſpect of God, our Sauiour. for this is good. 1. Tim. 2.3. O acceptable in his ſight. Pſal. 19.1. Baru. 3.33, 34. If all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, ſeeke to pleaſe God. Pſal. 104, 19. 7, 21, 32. Ierem. 8.7. Eſay. 1.3. Shall not man being more bound then they all. Gen. 1.26. 1. Pet. 1.19. 1. Cor. 3.16. Aphe. 2, 10. 2. Tim. 4.8. 1. Pet. 5.4.</note> pray for <hi>Caeſar,</hi> for ſayth Saint <hi>Paule, <hi>this is good and acceptable in the ſight of God our Sauiour:</hi>
                     </hi> If the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens</hi> declare the <hi>glorie</hi> of God, and the <hi>Firmament</hi> ſhew his <hi>handy-worke:</hi> If the <hi>Light</hi> obey him with <hi>feare:</hi> If the <hi>Starres</hi> ſhine in their <hi>Watch</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioice: If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Moone</hi> kéepe her appointed <hi>ſeaſons:</hi> If the <hi>Sun</hi> knoweth his <hi>going downe:</hi> If the <hi>waters</hi> flie at his <hi>rebuke:</hi> If the <hi>Lions</hi> ſeeke their meat at <hi>God:</hi> If <hi>hee</hi> looke on the <hi>Earth</hi> and it <hi>trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth:</hi> If <hi>hee</hi> touch the <hi>Mountaines</hi> and they <hi>ſmoke:</hi> If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Storke</hi> in the aire knoweth her appointed <hi>times,</hi> and the Turtle, and the Crane, and the <hi>Swallow</hi> obſerue the time of their comming? If the <hi>Oxe</hi> know his <hi>owner</hi> and the <hi>Aſſe</hi> his <hi>maiſters crib:</hi> ſhall not <hi>man</hi> being not <hi>liue-leſſe</hi> like <hi>ſome,</hi> not <hi>ſenceleſſe</hi> like <hi>others,</hi> not <hi>vnreaſonable</hi> like <hi>others;</hi> But <hi>created</hi> by a <hi>conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the deitie, <hi>redeemed</hi> with the precious <hi>bloud</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as of a <hi>Lamb vndefiled,</hi> &amp; without ſpot, <hi>ſanctified</hi> by the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> expecting a <hi>Crowne,</hi> a Crowne of <hi>life,</hi> a Crowne of <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes,</hi>
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:152155:63"/>
a Crowne of <hi>glory,</hi> performe to <hi>Caeſar</hi> all duetifull <hi>alleagiance,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Seeke in all things to pleaſe his Maieſtie. 1. Tim. 2.3.</note> ſince the <hi>bleſſed Apoſtle</hi> hath taught vs, <hi>that this is good, and acceptable in the ſight of God our Sauiour?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <p>THE <hi>eternall Father</hi> for his <hi>ſweet Sons ſake,</hi> by the <hi>holy ſpirit</hi> ſo rule our hearts,<note place="margin">The Authors prayer for Caeſar, and Caeſars true ſubiects. Iames. 5.16 2. King. 1.10, 12.</note> that we being righteous as <hi>Elias,</hi> and our prayers <hi>feruent</hi> as <hi>Elias,</hi> they may open <hi>heauen,</hi> &amp; bring from thence <hi>Gods Iudgements</hi> as <hi>fier</hi> vpon <hi>Caeſars</hi> enemies: but the <hi>dewe</hi> of the <hi>diuine grace</hi> vpon <hi>Caeſar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. King. 18, 45 Rom. 13.5.</note> and <hi>Caeſars</hi> true <hi>Subiects:</hi> that <hi>her</hi> moſt <hi>ſacred Maieſtie</hi> may <hi>long, religiouſly, happily</hi> rule vs, that we for <hi>conſcience ſake,</hi> leaſt we reſiſt <hi>the ordinance of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> God,</hi> leaſt we receue <hi>Iudgement,</hi> leaſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> we be depriued of all <hi>benefits</hi> inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> to the Loyall, <hi>Feare, Honor, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, Pay tribute to, Defend,</hi> and <hi>Pray</hi> for her moſt <hi>ſacred Maieſty</hi> on earth, and in <hi>the end,</hi> and without all <hi>end,</hi> raigne together with <hi>her</hi> in the kingdome of Heauen, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:152155:64"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152155:64"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
